<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catechist catechiz'd: or, Loyalty asserted in vindication of the oath of allegiance, against a new catechism set forth by a father of the Society of Jesus To which is annexed a decree, made by the fathers of the same Society, against the said oath: with animadversions upon it. By Adolphus Brontius, a Roman-Catholick.</title>
            <author>Cary, Edward, d. 1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222415</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833593</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35138)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2205:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catechist catechiz'd: or, Loyalty asserted in vindication of the oath of allegiance, against a new catechism set forth by a father of the Society of Jesus To which is annexed a decree, made by the fathers of the same Society, against the said oath: with animadversions upon it. By Adolphus Brontius, a Roman-Catholick.</title>
                  <author>Cary, Edward, d. 1711.</author>
                  <author>England. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>189, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1681</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Adolphus Brontius = Edward Cary.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Errata at foot of p. 189.</note>
                  <note>The oath is found in "An Act for the better discovering and repressing of Popish recusants".</note>
                  <note>"The Jesuits catechism: or, A brief instruction touching the oath of allegiance" and "The catechist catechiz'd: or, Loyalty asserted. In a letter to a father of the Society" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38071:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>The Catechiſt Catechiz'd:</hi> OR, LOYALTY ASSERTED.</p>
            <p>IN Vindication OF THE <hi>OATH</hi> of <hi>ALLEGIANCE,</hi> AGAINST A New <hi>Catechiſm</hi> ſet forth BY A Father of the Society of <hi>JESUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is Annexed A Decree, made by the Fathers of the ſame <hi>Society,</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>Oath:</hi> With <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>ADOLPHUS BRONTIUS,</hi> A Roman-Catholick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reddite quae ſunt Caeſaris Caeſari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1681.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38071:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38071:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE noiſe of this new Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, ſo rudely treating the Oath of Allegiance, and Miſ-ſhaping the beauty of Truth into the deformity of a Monſter, as it has excited the more Curious, both of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to enquire after it, ſo it has raiſed in both an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt it. Men run to the Stationer for it, but find it not. The truth is, this unhappy Catechiſm, though in Print, is not expoſed to Sail; for the Author, Conſcious to himſelf, that, like the night-bird, it will not endure publick Light, keeps it ſomewhat
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38071:3"/> in the dark, but yet imparts it to all his friends, and confidents: It's firſt Birth and Print was in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> where having had the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of ſome of his Society, [the never-failing Ecchoes of each others praiſes,] by them 'twas commended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o thoſe Monaſteries of Men and Women, upon which he has a great Aſcendent. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome few Copies were ſcattered in <hi>Paris;</hi> from whence, by the deſign of the Author, one was ſent to me; and now many more of them are ſtolen into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and put into the hands of Ladies; I ſuppoſe, to principle them, and their children, in his way of Loyalty. In any of my Engagements againſt him and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon this Subject, which have been many, theſe three laſt years, I never yet appeared in Print.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38071:3"/> Nor did I ever deſign it, till now; being partly importuned by his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prints, partly by Sollicitation of powerful friends, and moſt of all out of a duty to my Prince, and a juſt reſentment of the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to Catholick Religion. But it ſhall be with a juſtice ſo impartial, that it ſhall rather force him to an acknowledgment of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, in my proceſs againſt him, than incur the imputation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either injurious to him, or too indulgent to my ſelf. I ſhall therefore couple both the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and the Anſwer in one Print and Book, let them ſtand or fall by the reaſons they bring. And now Reader, whether I will or no, you will be judge betwixt us. If affection bribe your underſtanding, you wrong your ſelf, and us too; if reaſon weighs down the Scale
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38071:4"/> of your judgment, you ſhall do your ſelf right, and no wrong to any one. Be adviſed by holy Thomas of <hi>Kempis; Mind not who ſpeaks, but what is ſpoken.</hi> You have alſo here Annexed, a Decree made againſt this Oath, with Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon it. I commend it to your ſerious peruſal; Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group xml:lang="eng">
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38071:4"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>The Jeſuits Catechiſm:</hi> Or, A Brief INSTRUCTION Touching the OATH OF Allegiance.</p>
                  <p>By Way of DIALOGUE.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1681.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38071:5"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:38071:5"/>
                  <head>GENTLE READER.</head>
                  <p>THE Scourge of periury, of which theſe later years the Catholick cauſe lyes bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ought to have made Catholicks more Circumſpect in ſwearing: whereas divers by taking an unlawful oath, have encreaſed the evil. It was not, God knowns, the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> that could cure periury, no more then ſtabbing ones ſelf can heal the wound given by ones enemy. A falſe <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> may be treachery to Religion, but not <hi>Allegiance</hi> to ones King. And a Traytour to his Religion will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a faithful Subject to his Soveraign. He that by Oath will diſpenſe with his Honour and Conſcience in the firſt, will not long boggle at the ſecond. There may an equal intereſt appear in both, and then adieu to one as well as the other. Some who took the Oath, have ſince, to eaſe their fault, ſlept at a Miniſter's Sermon, and taken the cheering cup and Lord's Supper to help its digeſtion. Others made their <hi>Good man</hi> their <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſo renounced his <hi>Supremacy.</hi> The greateſt part hurried to Courts of Juſtice, and abuſed by the ſpecious title of <hi>Allegiance</hi> ſwore what they meant, and meant what was juſt, though their meaning was far from the words they ſwore to, and from the Obedience due to their Supream Paſtor.</p>
                  <p>The Refuſers of the Oath, by their adverſaries
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38071:6"/> are term'd diſloyal, and made conſpiring againſt the Old Catholick cauſe, for teaching the unlawfulneſs of an Oath, which they themſelves make to be no <hi>Allegiance,</hi> by ſaying, <hi>I ſwear not to the words, as they lye, but only my opinion.</hi> So that as without Diſpenſation I may change my opinion, I may change my <hi>Allegiance.</hi> But you know we are taught better things. Our <hi>Allegiance</hi> muſt live and dye with us, and we in the defence of his Majeſties Rights and Prerogatives. As we are ready to ſwear a promiſe of all due <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ſo we muſt not ſwear what we cannot, let it bear what title it will: he that cares not what he ſwears, cares not what he obſerves. <hi>The good old Cauſe</hi> bids you ſwear what you will; <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> or <hi>Allegiance;</hi> and do you know what. The good old Catholick cauſe bids you ſwear what is juſt, and do what you ſwear.</p>
                  <p>In defence of the refuſers of the Oath, I have framed this ſhort inſtruction by way of Dialogue; the cleareſt method, I could think of, to evidence the unlawfulneſs of the Oath, confirm the refuſers in their Chriſtian Reſolution, and reclaim ſuch as have been miſled; the only intent and deſire of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your faithful Servant, <hi>J. D.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38071:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Jeſuits Catechiſm:</hi> Or a Brief INSTRUCTION Touching the <hi>OATH</hi> of <hi>ALLEGIANCE,</hi> By way of Dialogue.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <head type="sub">The Matter is Stated.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>ARE you a Loyal Subject?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I am; nor doe I well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive why you queſtion it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I queſtion it, becauſe of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is Catholick.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>And becauſe of my Religion, I am the more bound to Loyalty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Wherein conſiſts Loyalty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>In a firm and conſtant reſolution of paying all due <hi>Allegiance</hi> to my Prince.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> a part of this Duty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, as far as it contains <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Why? does it contain any thing elſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38071:7"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Aſſuredly; it bears the Title of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance;</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> is the leaſt part of it; and the reſt cannot be ſworn to.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you then think the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> unlawful?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I judg it to be ſo.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>And Why?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe it hath not the requiſites of a lawful Oath.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>How can you make this good?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Firſt, by ſtating the Requiſits to a lawful Oath. 2. By conſidering the Oath as contain'd under the Title of the Act of Parliament enjoyning the tendring it. 3. By ſingling out what in the Oath it ſelf falls ſhort of thoſe Requiſites. 4. By the Popes prohibiting of the ſaid. Oath.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Of the Requiſites to a lawful Oath.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat is an Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is a calling God to witneſs what I Affirm or Promiſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>How many ſorts of Oaths are there?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>An Oath (as to our purpoſe) is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: Aſſertory and Promiſory.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38071:7"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is an Aſſertory Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is to ſwear a thing to be true, in order to be believ'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is a Promiſory?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is to ſwear a Promiſe, in order to bind our ſelves to another.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>In which of theſe two Oaths, does an Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> conſiſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>In a promiſory, as is clear; for by a promiſe alone I bind my <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is the Engliſh Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> wholly Promiſory?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No; the greateſt part is meerly ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative, and Aſſertory; and therefore no Oath of <hi>Allegiance:</hi> ſo that the Title ill becomes the whole; and ſeems only put to draw in People.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Set me down the Conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for the Lawfulneſs of an Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are three; <hi>Truth, Lawfulneſs</hi> of the thing to be ſworn, and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of ſwearing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What do you mean by <hi>Truth?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I mean that I muſt underſtand the words I ſwear by, and that I muſt have a moral certainty that the thing is ſo as I ſwear it to be: which certainty admits no doubt of the thing's being otherwiſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is not the probability of a thing's
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38071:8"/> being ſo, enough for one to ſwear it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No; for probability leaving a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional doubt, whether the thing be ſo or no, I cannot bring God's veracity to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs what I doubt of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>May not I upon a probability of a thing's being ſo, ſwear I think it is ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I may, becauſe the Oath is then grounded, upon the certainty I have of my Thought, tho' never ſo weak; and not upon the probability of the thing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray come to the 2. Requiſit: what do you mean by the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of a thing?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I mean that the thing be neither unlawful in it ſelf as the telling of a lye; nor by prohibition, as eating Fleſh upon <hi>Friday?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What do you underſtand in the third Requiſite by <hi>Neceſſity?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I mean that one muſt not ſwear lightly, but by reaſon of ſome Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grounded in a vertue, as <hi>Charity, Justice,</hi> or <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Of which of theſe requiſites does the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> fail?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It fails of all. It fails of <hi>Truth,</hi> which is the firſt; becauſe many Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſons, do not underſtand the force
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38071:8"/> of the words and thoſe who underſtand them, have no moral certainty of the truth of the things ſignifi'd by them. It fails of the 2. Requiſit, that is the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of the thing I ſwear: <hi>Firſt,</hi> by reaſon this Oath obliges me to unlawful Diſcoveries. <hi>Secondly,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is prohibited by a lawful power; and <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by being made a mark of Religion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſay you to the 3. Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, which is <hi>Neceſſity?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It appears from the want of the two firſt requiſits. For it is ſo far from the requiſit of Neceſſity, as that it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary not to take it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You ſeem then to hold this Oath cannot be taken without a grievous ſin, and without Perjury?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is but what two Popes have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared with ſeveral Breves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is Perjury?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is a calling God to witneſs a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>In what conſiſts it's Malice?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>In making God, who is Truth it ſelf, Witneſs of an untruth, and as it were Perjured; he being his own Oath in what he witneſſes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38071:9"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is Perjury a great ſin?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes: a hainous one; and ſo againſt Nature, as the very Gentiles, the Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians and Aegyptians put the Perjured to Death, the Indians cut off their Hands and Feet.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Of the Title of the Act.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat is the Title of the Act, which orders the tendring the Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is <hi>An Act for the diſcovering and ſuppreſſing Popiſh Recuſants.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What do you infer from this Title?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I infer what is naturally Inferr'd from a Title, the intent of the Act, which is; <hi>to diſcover and ſuppreſs Popiſh Recuſants</hi> by means of the Oath.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you then think the Oath to be intended, as a diſtinctive ſign of Popery?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes; for what ever is ordered to <hi>Diſcover</hi> and <hi>Suppreſs</hi> Popiſh Recuſants, muſt be intended to diſtinguiſh them from others.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo? Are there not other things enjoin'd by the Act to diſtinguſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38071:9"/> 
                           <hi>Recuſants,</hi> as the going to Church, to Communion <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may verify the Title of the Act?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>There are but thoſe things diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Diſſenters in General, who refuſe the Proteſtant Communion, and Church, no leſs than Catholicks. The Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> is only proper to try Catholiks, and therefore chiefly pointed at by the Title.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Have you conſidered the <hi>Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in the Act prefixed to the Oath, it may perchance alter your Opinion?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I believe not. I pray deliver it me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>It runs thus: <hi>And for the better tryal how his Majeſtyes Subjects ſtand Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in point of Loyalty and due Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, be it alſo Enacted, &amp;c.</hi> By which words you ſee the intent is, to diſtinguſh Loyal, from diſloyal Subjects, and not what you pretend from the Title of the Act.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Be it ſaid with your good leave, this preamble Confirms the Oath to be, not only a diſtinctive ſign to <hi>diſcover</hi> a Papiſt, but adds to the Diſcovery a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty the greateſt imaginable, of making a Papiſt to be reputed and perſecuted as <hi>Diſloyal,</hi> and conſequently to be <hi>ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38071:10"/> as is deſigned in the Title.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is then the Title of the Act fitly and fully apply'd to the Oath, ſince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are contain'd in the Act?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes; for a Papiſt is <hi>Diſcover'd</hi> by his Refuſal; and his refuſal of the Oath brings him in <hi>Diſloyal,</hi> and expoſes him as ſuch to the Laws to be <hi>Suppreſs'd;</hi> which is the full intention of the Act, for ſo are compleated the two parts of the Title; to <hi>Diſcover</hi> and <hi>Suppreſs:</hi> From this you muſt neceſſarily infer, that this Law which ſettles Proteſtant Religion, by the words, <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands and aims at nothing but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with that Religion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Can you make this out by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtance contained in the Act, and prove that this Oath is intended for a diſtinction of Religion, and not only a diſtinction of Loyalty?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, I can; if you allow Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and going to Church to be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctive mark of Religion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I allow them for ſuch.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>If ſo, be pleaſed to reflect, how the ſame Act does declare that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is propoſed for a diſtinctive ſign of Loyalty, and Obedience; and not for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38071:10"/> a ſign of Religion, for the <hi>Preamble</hi> to the ordaining the taking of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this: <hi>For the better diſcovery there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ſuch Perſons, and their evil Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Kings Majeſty, and the ſtate of the Realm, to the end that evil purpoſes may be better prevented, be it Enacted, that once in every Year following, he receive the Lords Supper.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>This is ſomthing; for, if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Communion be a diſtinctive ſign of Religion, although the <hi>Preamble</hi> might be produced to perſwade the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and that it is only a diſtinctive ſign of Loyalty; ſo the taking the Oath is clearly a diſtinctive ſign to diſcover a Papiſt as the Title does declare, though the <hi>Preamble</hi> alledged ſeem to bear ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intent. Nor can I invent a Reaſon, when I compare the two <hi>Preambles,</hi> why this latter <hi>Preamble</hi> ſhould not be as Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious to exempt Communion from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mark of Religion, and make it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſign of Loyalty, as the former is to exclude the Oath from being a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſign; as both this Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by its Title, and the Popes Breves declare it to be. So that I am yours: and only add, the joyning ſuch things as the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38071:11"/> Oath and Communion together, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declares the meaning of the Title and the Law-makers intention <hi>of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and ſuppreſſing Popiſh Recuſants</hi> by means of this Oath.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>This being ſo; I cannot in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience take it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray come to the particulars of the Oath in it ſelf?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is my duty to comply with your juſt commands.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                     <head type="sub">The Aſſertory part of the Oath conſidered in two Clauſes.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>DEſcend to thoſe particulars, that render the Oath unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelf.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are more than one; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt lay down a Method to be the clearer.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>As you pleaſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Firſt then I divide this Oath into its Aſſertory part, and its promiſſory: an Aſſertory Oath as I have told you, is to ſwear a thing to be true in order
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38071:11"/> to be believed: and this Aſſertory Oath, as is evident, includes no promiſe of Fidelity; and by Conſequence is no Oath of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Produce the firſt Clauſe you ſay cannot be ſworn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſhall place firſt, what in the Oath is with deſign placed laſt, but influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences upon all that goes before it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are theſe words following: <hi>And all thoſe things, I do plainly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerly acknowledge, and ſwear according to theſe expreſs words by me ſpoken, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the plain and common ſenſe and underſtanding of the ſame words, without any equivocation, or mentall evaſions, or ſecret reſervation whatſoever.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What difficulty find you in theſe words?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The difficulty is: that after I have ſworn, what cannot be ſworn according to the expreſs words, and without ſome reſervation, I am engaged to forſwear all reſervation, in what I have ſworn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is that which cannot be ſworn according to the expreſs words and without any reſervation?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Give me leave to propoſe unto you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38071:12"/> by way of doubt the enſuing Clauſe, though never ſo plauſible in appearance. <hi>I teſtify and declare in my Conſcience before God and the world, that our Soveraign, KING CHARLES, is lawful and Rightful KING of the Realm, and all other his Majeſties Dominions and Countries.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I cannot conceive any reaſon, you have to ſtumble at this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>My firſt reaſon, is, a due reſpect to his Majeſty; the 2. is, that I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not perfectly what I am to ſwear, nor have a Moral certainty of the truth of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is not this an affected pretence to cloak diſobedience?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Were it ſo, I ſhould not ſwear as I do in theſe expreſs foregoing words, <hi>I truly and ſincerely acknowledg, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs;</hi> that is, interiourly, and exteriourly own by words and deeds, <hi>Our Soveraign King Charles to be lawful King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Are not the words <hi>I teſtify</hi> and <hi>declare</hi> as neceſſary to my <hi>Allegiance</hi> as the other?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No they are Derogatory to his Majeſty, and by Conſequence to my <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>My thinks you are harping upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38071:12"/> a tickliſh point, wherefore I pray ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain your ſelf better.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>To testify</hi> as importing ſomthing diſtinct from my <hi>acknowledging</hi> in the rigour of the <hi>expreſs word</hi> is to bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; to <hi>declare,</hi> as diſtinct from <hi>profeſſing,</hi> is as it were to act the part of a Judg, in Clearing a thing not ſo well known, and is it not to queſtion the right of a King, to call the Subject, and ſwear him a witneſs of it? are witneſſes ſworn but in Caſe of Controverſy? or are declarations required, but in Caſe of doubt? the King is King, by his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared indiſputable right. This right, without any more makes the Subject a Subject. To ſwear me to witneſs he is my King after my acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his right, is as it were to make him own his right to my acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment; whereas my acknowledgment is a tribute due to his right; which has no need of my witneſſing or declaring it, as the Tenor of the Oath ſeems to ſuppoſe it hath; by requiring me to be a witneſs and declarer of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You are a very preciſe ſwearer?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No preciſer, then I am ſworn to be by the expreſs words I am to ſwear
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38071:13"/> to, without any Reſervation, which obliges me to diſcuſs exactly the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of them; and I find thoſe words I <hi>testify</hi> and <hi>declare</hi> in their natural ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent rather prejudicial to his Majeſties right, and my <hi>Alletrance,</hi> than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Have you any other reaſon againſt this Clauſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I have; my 2<hi>d.</hi> reaſon is, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perſon, as moſt are, to whom the Oath is tendred, not well verſed in matters of State and Juſtice, am forced to ſwear things which are above me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What are thoſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I am ſworn to <hi>teſtify, and declare before God and the world, that our Soveraign Lord King Charles is Lawful King of this Realm and all other his Majesties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countries.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I fear you are more nice, than Conſcientious, what difficulty can you find in this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>My difficulty is, that I know not what I ſwear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you not know he is your Lawful King?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I know and ſwear it too. Let every
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38071:13"/> Subject of his reſpective Dominions and Country do the ſame; but do I who am an Idiot know, what is meant by <hi>all other his Majeſties Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries?</hi> Do I know what they are, and the right to them? have I Moral Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what I ſwear to? his Title runs: <hi>King of England, Scotland, France and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he poſſeſſes many places in <hi>Affrica,</hi> and <hi>America;</hi> ſome Dominions have been changed ſince the framing of this Oath. I am not certain of the Juſtice of his Titles to all, and therefore as a faithful Subject upon probable Motives will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it, will ſwear to ſtand for it, which is true <hi>Allegiance,</hi> but for want of certainty of the right he hath to all, cannot ſwear it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I did not expect you would have inſiſted upon this Clauſe; however I muſt own you cannot be too nice in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what you ſwear, being clogg'd with the firſt Clauſe of ſwearing to the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> words, without any <hi>Reſervation</hi> whatſoever.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:38071:14"/>
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <hi>Of</hi> 2. <hi>more Clauſes of the Aſſertory part.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>THe third Clauſe, <hi>I declare in my Conſcience before God, that the Pope neither of himſelf, nor by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, with any other, can depoſe the King.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What exception make you againſt this Clauſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The want of Truth, which makes me perjured, if I without any reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſwear to the <hi>plain and common under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the ſame words.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is the common and plain ſence of the words, as they lye?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>This propoſition. <hi>The Pope by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means with any other can depoſe the King,</hi> is expreſly the ſame as this; <hi>No body can depoſe the King,</hi> that is, <hi>no Pope, no King, no Emperour, no Prince,</hi> which you ſee is againſt the dayly practiſe of war, in which victory depoſes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd party from ſome part of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Nothing is intended by theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38071:14"/> words, witneſs the Law-maker, but that the Pope, by no Papal or Eccleſiaſtical Authority can depoſe the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Do the expreſs words of the Oath bear this reſervation? Do they not expreſly exclude it? The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Pope himſelf,</hi> of <hi>the Church,</hi> and of the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> are they not foreſworn in the foregoing words? which being ſworn to, what can theſe words, <hi>nor by any other means with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> imply?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What are the preceding words?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are theſe, <hi>and that the Pope neither of himſelf nor by any Authority of the Church or See of Rome,</hi> &amp;c. I beſeech you, reflect upon the words, and then tell me. Can <hi>other</hi> that is different <hi>means</hi> from the <hi>Authority of Pope and Church,</hi> be the ſame with the <hi>Authority of Pope and Church?</hi> Can God himſelf make <hi>you</hi> and <hi>another</hi> to be the ſame? And if he cannot, what Law-maker can enable me to ſwear according to the plain ſenſe of the expreſs words <hi>the Pope and an other;</hi> and that the <hi>means of Eccleſiaſtical Authority</hi> and other <hi>means,</hi> are the ſame, which he muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do who will perſwade me, that to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38071:15"/> deny <hi>one</hi> and to deny the <hi>other</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to expreſs words, is no more than to deny one and the ſame thing?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>This is ſo clear, that nothing but a previous wilful engagement to the contrary can obſcure it. Why did not the Law-maker make his interpretation a part of the <hi>expreſs words,</hi> as he has made the expreſs words an excluſion of his interpretation, and the only Subject of my Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The fourth Clauſe is; <hi>No Perſon whatſoever has Power to abſolve me from this Oath:</hi> this Clauſe according to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the words, is no truer than the former, and therefore cannot be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſworn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Shew why it cannot be ſworn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe the King, by quitting his Crown, may quit me of my <hi>Allegiance:</hi> Is he no body? Should the King and Parliament diſmember a part of the Realm where I am Native, and make it over to a Forreign Prince, am not I free from my <hi>Allegiance?</hi> and are they no perſon whatſoever? doth not the power of Victory transfer <hi>Allegiance</hi> from one King to another? and the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring part, is he no body?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38071:15"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Should the King quit his Crown he might too repent himſelf as ſoon bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſayes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>That's much to the purpoſe. God ſend him long to live and Reign, but would his repentance unperſon him, and make him no body?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But the common ſenſe is, that no perſon from Rome can abſolve me of my <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The common ſenſe of the words, whatſoever the maker of the Oath might intend, bear no ſuch expoſition, but with a clear Negative exclude it, for no <hi>perſon whatſoever,</hi> in its natural ſenſe, is equivalent to this, <hi>No Pope, no King, no Prince</hi> can abſolve em; which is evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe, as hath been made out, and cannot be ſworn.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is not Victory, and the Kings quitting the Crown, equivalent to death, and the <hi>Succeſſion of an Heir,</hi> which, it's manifeſt, cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by theſe words <hi>no perſon whatſoever?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No: for death which is a pure Negation, only takes away the perſon from the dignity, and not the dignity from the perſon, as the King might do from himſelf; and ſucceſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ſo far
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38071:16"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38071:16"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:38071:17"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38071:17"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="28" facs="tcp:38071:18"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38071:18"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="30" facs="tcp:38071:19"/> from depoſing, that it is a continuation of the Predeceſſours right.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                     <head type="sub">
                        <hi>Of the</hi> 5. <hi>Clauſe of the Aſſertory Part.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>WHat elſe have you to ſay againſt the Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The 5. Clauſe is: <hi>I farther from my heart, abhor, detest, and abjure, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, this damnable Doctrine, and poſition, that Princes which are excommunicated or deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed, or murthered by their Subjects, or any whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What is't you ſcruple at?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſcruple at more than one thing; for it contains ſeveral things repugnant to Faith.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>If what you ſay, you make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be true, you will juſtify the Popes Breves, who affirm what you ſay; you will ſtop your adverſaries mouth, who boaſt you cannot after long po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, pick any thing out of the Oath, which is contrary to Faith, and you will clear your ſelf of Diſloyalty in refuſing it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:38071:19"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The firſt thing <hi>contrary to Faith,</hi> is for a ſecular Power, much more a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, to uſurp the Supremacy due to the Church in deciding what is <hi>Heretical,</hi> as the Parliament do's by tendring this Clauſe. From this it follows that 2. the complyance in ſwearing that Clauſe is alſo <hi>contrary to Faith,</hi> as being an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of that power. 3. It is <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Faith,</hi> to make the Doctrine of Depoſing, <hi>Heretical;</hi> it never having been condemned by the Church. 4. It is <hi>contrary to Faith</hi> to make an Article of Faith what is not, as it would be to ſay, it is Article of Faith that <hi>the Pope cannot depoſe a Prince in a Caſe of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and revolt from the Church.</hi> For this muſt be of faith, if the contradictory be <hi>Heretical;</hi> as it would not be <hi>Heretical</hi> to deny <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> if <hi>Tranſubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> were not an Article of faith. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what is implyed in the whole Clauſe, it is againſt faith to hold it Lawful to ſwear a thing to be <hi>Heretical</hi> which is not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Doth not the reſult of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Stilling-fleet, and others, who fall foul upon Catholicks for this Doctrine of depoſing?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:38071:20"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No, for as it is not <hi>Heretical,</hi> ſo it is no part of <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi> Nor doth any man as a Catholick believe it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not more favourable to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to hold it is <hi>Heretical?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It cannot be favourable to any one to hold an untruth.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>How can a Prince ſecure himſelf from that Doctrine?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>By a promiſſory Oath of never holding it, nor teaching it, though it be not <hi>Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But by your good leave, this is not ſo binding, as to ſwear it to be <hi>Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is more binding; for having ſworn it to be <hi>Heretical,</hi> if afterwards I find it not to be <hi>Heretical,</hi> as one will eaſily do, I am freed from my Oath, as having ſworn an untruth; but when I promiſe by Oath never to follow it, nor teach it, be it <hi>Heretical</hi> or no, I have no ſuch evaſion, as is manifeſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You have acquitted your ſelf as to this point, but may not the particle, <hi>as Heretical,</hi> make this ſenſe that I abjure that doctrine as if it were <hi>Heretical</hi> or like an <hi>Hereſie?</hi> As it is ſaid, <hi>I hate him as a Toad, I love him as my Father.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not deny but that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38071:20"/> ſenſe of the particle <hi>as</hi> ſomtimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes <hi>ſimilitude</hi> or equality, but it is when it relates to different Subjects; for example let him <hi>be unto thee as a heathen.</hi> But this is not our preſent Caſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I ſee it is not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Sometimes the particle <hi>as</hi> implyes the reality of a thing being ſo; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; a paper as ſeditious was burnt, ſignifyes its reality of being ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray give me a General Rule, when the particle <hi>as</hi> in common ſpeech, has this ſecond ſignification.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The beſt I can give you, as to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe, is; it generally implies the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a thing being ſo, as often as it applyes an <hi>Adjective</hi> to a <hi>Subſtantive;</hi> for the <hi>Adjective</hi> not being able to ſtand without the <hi>Subſtantive.</hi> the particle <hi>as</hi> makes the <hi>Adjective</hi> fall upon the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive.</hi> I do not diſapprove of your Rule, exemplify it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is our preſent Caſe. When I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure a Doctrine as <hi>Heretical,</hi> the particle <hi>as</hi> caſts the Adjective <hi>Heretical,</hi> upon the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which is its ſubſtantive, and implies the Doctrine to be Hererical.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:38071:21"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But ſhould you grant the Particle <hi>as</hi> might imply <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> as it doth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of being <hi>Heretical,</hi> might I reſtrain it to ſimilitude?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No; for in your ſuppoſition the particle <hi>as</hi> being in its common ſenſe indifferent to both, I muſt ſwear both.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Why ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe I muſt ſwear without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not true, that words are to be ſworn in the ſenſe which renders the Law juſt? and that a penal Law is to be interpreted in the moſt favourable ſenſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is true in ſome other Caſes, but not in this where by the expreſs words of the Oath, all evaſions, interpretations, and reſervations, are excluded; would it not be ridiculous, for the Law or Law-maker, to give me leave by uſing reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, to forſwear my ſelf?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Methinks the word <hi>Heretical</hi> may ſignify <hi>material Hereſy.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>You tire me out with theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions, and I tell you again I muſt ſwear without any reſtriction whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I have a better evaſion then any of theſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:38071:21"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>You are reſolved to try my pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if it be an evaſion, which the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words afford you not, you abjure it. However I pray make it known.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Be it true or not true, that the Pope can abſolve me from my Oath, be it true or not true, that the Doctrin of depoſing is <hi>Heretical,</hi> I may yet ſwear <hi>I think the Pope cannot abſolve me, I think that Doctrine is Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not I ſwear theſe things in the ſame nature as <hi>I ſwear King Charles to be my Lawful King?</hi> I do as is manifeſt; and when I ſwear him to be ſo, do I only ſwear I think he is my Lawful King? to ſwear at the Barr <hi>I think one guilty,</hi> is no good evidence; to ſwear <hi>that one is guilty</hi> is a good evidence; by which it appears how much difference there is in my ſwearing <hi>it is ſo,</hi> and <hi>I think it is ſo.</hi> Where do you find in the whole Oath, ſo much as the word <hi>I think?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You <hi>profeſs in your Conſcience,</hi> that is, according to your judgment, is not that as much, as to ſwear you think it is ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is moſt certain, my Judgment or Conſcience muſt direct me to ſwear,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38071:22"/> otherwiſe my Oath would be irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; but this Conſcience may direct me to ſwear a Doctrine to be <hi>Heretical,</hi> may direct me to ſwear <hi>I think it is Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal;</hi> which are two different things, and it cannot be made out of the Oath, that I ſwear <hi>I think it is Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You have reaſon; and you might reflect, how the Oath-teachers by this evaſion, without any diſpenſation from the Pope, keep their <hi>Allegiance</hi> at their own diſpoſal, as to this Aſſertory part.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>How ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe it hangs upon the hinge of a thought ready to be turned any way. I ſwear I think it is ſo, and not being certain that it is, for example, that King Charles is my King, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of depoſing is Heretical, in the next hour, upon new Motives, I may change my thought, and with my thought my <hi>Allegiance:</hi> for my thought I ſwear to, is not grounded in a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of truth (as A. B. ownes in his 3. letter) for were one certain of the truth, he might ſwear the things to be true in themſelves which A. B. a chief Oath-teacher denys to do.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38071:22"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Me thinks this is very clear, which makes me inferr moreover, that this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, is injurious to his Majeſty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>For what reaſon?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>By reaſon it ownes I do not ſwear <hi>as true in it ſelf, that King Charles is my Lawful King;</hi> but that I think only he is, which includes a doubt of his being ſo; for were I certain, I might ſwear he is my Lawful King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>From whence do you inferr this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe according to the Oathiſts Confeſſion, I do not ſwear <hi>as true in it ſelf the Doctrine of depoſing to be Heretical.</hi> Now the words of the Oath falling e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually on both, if they do not affirm as true in it ſelf the one, they do not the other.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Am I then obliged to ſwear <hi>as true in it ſelf, that King Charles is my Lawful King?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I am if the King exacts it; for I have as Phyſical, and moral evidence of his being my King, and King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as I have of his being owned by the whole world, without any one laying claim to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Have not I the ſame evidence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38071:23"/> that the Doctrine of depoſing is <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No: I have evidence to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for it is evident the Church, has never defined it to be <hi>Heretical.</hi> A pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſon's, nor a whole univerſity's, declaring it to be againſt the word of God does not make it Heretical. Let men examin what the <hi>Sorbon's</hi> opinion was concerning this point in <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and Henry the fourth's time, and of the Siege of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you then certain the Doctrine of depoſing is not <hi>Heretical?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I am: as I am certain there is no definition of the Church to make it ſo; from which certainty, I conclude <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as rationally</hi> think it <hi>Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal;</hi> for can I be certain a thing is not <hi>Heretical</hi> and yet think it is <hi>Heretical,</hi> and if I cannot think it is <hi>Heretical,</hi> how can I ſwear it to be <hi>Heretical,</hi> or that I think it to be ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Did not the French Jeſuits ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Cenſure of the depoſing Doctrine <hi>as being contrary to the word of God,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Whether they did or did not, it ſerves for nothing, but to bring an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38071:23"/> upon them. Did they ſubſcribe the depoſing Doctrine was Heretical? what harm for peace ſake to ſubſcribe an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion? did they declare the oppoſite opinion to be an Article of Faith, did they ſwear, the opinion to be Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; did they ſubſcribe that opinion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more than as an opinion, and by way of opinion?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You have ſaid a great deal, and no more than what is true, draw your concluſion from what has been ſaid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is: that I can neither ſwear the Doctrine of depoſing to be <hi>Heretical;</hi> nor, that <hi>I think it to he Heretical,</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a certainty it is not <hi>Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Another evaſion anſwer'd.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>IN the firſt place, I conjure you to lay aſide all Logical School-Terms, and ſubtleties, and clear the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty ſo (as I may ſay) that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reading it, before he goes a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, may underſtand it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I can do no more, than promiſe the beſt of my endeavour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38071:24"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>The evaſion is, that this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>A Prince excommunicated or deprived by the Pope may be depoſed or murdered by his Subjects, or any one whatſoever, is Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical.</hi> Therefore I may ſwear it to be <hi>Heretical.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>This propoſition, as being expoſed to Quibbles, is not proper to be ſworn by every Idiot, who muſt perfectly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what he ſwears to, or he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelf to Perjury.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not clear that it is <hi>Heretical</hi> to ſay a Prince excommunicated may be murthered?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Grant it is, how comes the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, ſaying, A Prince excommunicated may be depoſed, to be <hi>Heretical.</hi> Who has defined it ſo to be?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>The propoſition, as affirming both together to be lawful, is Heretical.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>That is not the ſenſe of the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but to the truth of it, is required, that <hi>the propoſition ſaying one, or the other to be lawful, be Heretical:</hi> and the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, ſaying the one, that is <hi>Depoſing,</hi> is not <hi>Heretical?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray clear it a little better if you can.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is clear, by the words themſelves; for by the words of the Oath, I do not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38071:24"/> ſwear the propoſition, ſaying, <hi>A Prince excommunicated may be depoſed and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</hi> but <hi>may be depoſed or murthered,</hi> to be <hi>Heretical;</hi> which in the common way of ſpeaking are wholly different. By the firſt is ſworn, to teach the Lawfulneſs of both together to be <hi>Heretical;</hi> and the Lawfulneſs of both together, implying <hi>Murthering</hi> to be lawful, is truly <hi>Heretical.</hi> By the ſecond is ſworn, to teach Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the one, which is of <hi>Depoſing,</hi> or the other, that is <hi>Murthering,</hi> to be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, which is falſe; for the ſaying, <hi>it is lawful to depoſe an excommunicated Prince</hi> is not Heretical.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You have ſaid as much for clearing this caſe, as the expreſs words afford you, according to which one is to ſwear.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I only add, that, if the Oath-teachers can give any interpretation ſo connatural to the expreſs words as I have done, he that takes the Oath, being ſworn to wave all Reſervation, muſt ſwear to both, which without Perjury he cannot. After ſo many real difficulties againſt the Lawfulneſs of the Oath, I cannot but enquire, how one can take theſe laſt two Clauſes of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertory part; firſt, that <hi>it is adminiſtred to me by good and lawful power,</hi> the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38071:25"/> what is Hereſy appertaining to the Catholick Church, and not to a Proteſtant Parliament. The ſecond, <hi>And I do make this Recognition and Acknowledgment, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, willingly and truly, upon the Faith of a Chriſtian, ſo help me God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Of the Promiſſory part of the Oath.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>THe Aſſertory part of the Oath, is it any part of <hi>Allegiance?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is not.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Then the greateſt part of this Oath, is intitled from <hi>Allegiance,</hi> contains <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> as the leaſt part of it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>You ſay no more than what I have often anſwered. From which you may infer, that by the Oath, ſomething more than <hi>Allegiance</hi> was intended.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is it not a part of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your <hi>King?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>It is no part of <hi>Allegiance</hi> to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg Him by a <hi>thought,</hi> and a ſwearing <hi>I think ſo;</hi> but it is to acknowledge Him by a promiſſory Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which ſuppoſes a certainty of His being my true <hi>King.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:38071:25"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Are you ready to ſwear all the promiſſory part of the Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I am, except only the promiſe of <hi>diſcovering</hi> what is contained by Law, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the word <hi>Treaſon;</hi> which I cannot do without betraying my Religion, and he that will be a Traytor to his Religion, upon the like Motives will be a Traytor to his <hi>King.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What are thoſe things?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are. Firſt to maintain or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll Authority in the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> the 2. time is high treaſon, 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. <hi>2dly.</hi> to obtain or put in ure any Bull from <hi>Rome, high treaſon,</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. Thirdly, for Jeſuit or Prieſt made by Authority of the Pope, to come or remain in the King's Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions <hi>high treaſon</hi> 27 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 78. <hi>4thly.</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, or reconcile or to be reconciled to the Roman Religion, <hi>High treaſon.</hi> 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Jacob.</hi> 4. for this laſt <hi>Burnet</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned few years ſince, and ſeveral meerly for being Prieſts have lately been executed. So that thoſe Laws are yet in rigour.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you then think the aforeſaid things are ſignify'd by the word Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>How can I think otherwiſe? for the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38071:26"/> ſignification of words, is taken from the will of men, they being indifferent of their own nature to ſignify any thing, and the will of men cannot be more clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed than by their Laws; ſo that the moſt certain ſignification of a word, is what it hath by Law. This is ſo evident that no Philoſopher, no divine, no Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, ever yet called it in queſtion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides is it not made a diſtinct member from conſpiracies?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I have heard ſome ſay, to be Prieſts, and the like, are but Spiritual Treaſons.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Spiritual Treaſons that hang a man corporally. Are Spiritual Treaſons, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or no? is not this an evaſion? and are not all evaſions abjured? beſides all Spiritual power in oppoſition to the Pope being by the Law of the Nation ſetled in the King as part of his right, as it is <hi>treaſon</hi> to own extern power oppoſit to his right in temporals, ſo is it not <hi>treaſon</hi> according to the Law, to own the Popes power oppoſit to his right in his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals? the common ſenſe of the word <hi>Treaſon,</hi> can it be better derived, than from the common Law?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But doth not King <hi>James</hi> declare, that he intends nothing by the Oath than
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38071:26"/> the ſecuring himſelf from the depoſing power, and the dangerous principles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing from it, and that he exacts nothing but a civil <hi>Allegiance?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Under ſuch a pretence, might not I as well be ſworn to renounce the Pope, and my Religion, as be bound to take an unlawful Oath? would not that ſecure him as much as the Oath? The greateſt ſecurity he could have he might have had by a promiſſory Oath of never following that opinion; this never was deny'd him, nor will be deny'd his Succeſſours; his reſervation of civil <hi>Allegiance</hi> is excluded by the expreſs words of the Oath, which he himſelf obliges me to ſwear to. Would it not argue a ſtrange power to grant me leave to ſwear to an Interpretation, and by the ſame Oath to exclude it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Cannot then the Law-maker diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe in his own act?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>He may diſpenſe with me from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Oath, but ſuppoſing the Law, by his order or permiſſion, inforces the Oath upon me, the Law-maker cannot diſpenſe with me to ſwear in a different ſenſe from what the expreſs words bear. Nay doth not the Law-makers bringing an Interpretation, own the unlawfulneſs of the expreſs words?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38071:27"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Have you any thing elſe to inſtance for what you ſay?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I have, if you will be pleaſed to tell me, how the charge of the Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral runs againſt a Prieſt, condemned purely for Prieſt-hood.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Forasmuch as I have been able to gather out of the Trials of ſuch as have been condemned, the charge runs thus. <hi>As a falſe Traitor to our Soveraign Lord the King.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>So that one for being a Prieſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, is a <hi>falſe Traitor,</hi> that is guilty of <hi>Treaſon.</hi> And, conſequently, I ſwearing to diſcover all <hi>Treaſon</hi> ſwear to diſcover all Prieſts to ſome Informer, and to concur with the intent, and title of the Act of Parliament <hi>to the diſcovering and ſuppreſſing Popiſh Recuſants.</hi> What can be thought of more repugnant to faith?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You have quieted me as to this point, yet I have one demand to make.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>What is that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You know divers miſled, ſome for intereſt, ſome for other ends, ſome for want of due Reflection have taken the Oath, are they therefore bound to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Prieſts?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No, no more than <hi>Herod</hi> was obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38071:27"/> to cut off St. <hi>John's</hi> head. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is that ſuch a diſcovery being unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and damnable in it ſelf, an Oath which is a ſacred act of Religion, cannot be a bond of iniquity, and oblige me to what is unlawful.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I am ready to ſubſcribe, that you have made good the unlawfulneſs of the Oath. Firſt by reaſon of the <hi>title</hi> of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament exacting it; 2. For want of <hi>truth</hi> in all the clauſes of the aſſertory part. 3. For want of <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the clauſe of the promiſſory part. Laſtly, for want of <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity;</hi> there being a neceſſity under a grievous ſin, as the Pope declares, for the not taking it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I could not fail of your approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what I learned of you.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                     <head type="sub">Of the Pope's prohibition of the Oath of Allegiance.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>IS not the Pope our Soveraign Judg in Spirituals?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes: as our King in Temporals.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Why am I rather to obey the Pope
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38071:28"/> in refuſing the Oath than the King in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Becauſe the lawfulneſs or unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an Oath, as a point of Conſcience, lies within the verge, not of a Temporal, but of a Spiritual Juriſdiction.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Hath not the King the right to tender an Oath of <hi>Allegiance?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>He has, but this Oath contains much more than <hi>Allegiance</hi> in it, which renders it unlawful.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Hath the Pope no Prerogative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other Judges?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, according to the general ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Catholicks, he has that of Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in points of Doctrine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Do you hold the Pope Infallible?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I do, but not as an Article of Faith, becauſe it has never been defined by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, though I judge it defina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>In what degree then do you hold it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>I hold it with a great certainty: not being able to doubt of the contrary. For, who can think the Rock can fall? who can judge efficacious Chriſt's prayer for <hi>Peter,</hi> that his Faith might not fail? who can imagin that the ſpirit of Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38071:28"/> which aſſiſts the whole Church, ſhould abandon the Head of it? who can ſurmiſe that Chriſt who tenderd his Church above his own Life, ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit its Paſtor, not to feed it, but to poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it with falſe Doctrine?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I muſt interrupt you, for I know you might, and would ſay much more as to this point, and ſolve the difficulty to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; but you have ſaid enough to infer that if ſubmiſſion be due to other Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges who are Fallible, it is without doubt due to the Pope, who has too much reaſon to be judged Infallible. But not to bring more into Diſpute, than what purely concerns the Oath, ſuppoſing him as Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible as other Judges, is he not to be Obeyed?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The caſe being ſuppoſed equal, if he may be diſobeyed in points of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, why may not ſecular Judges be diſobey'd in Temporalls, and ſo adue all Government and Loyalty.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Though Judges be ſuppoſed Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, are not private perſons as fallible as they?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Much more Fallible, as being byas'd by Intereſt, Paſſion, and Engagement which are not ſo incident to Judges.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:38071:29"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>What if a Judge be miſinformed, doth his ſentence hold?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>His ſentence holds until ſuch time as that ſentence be repealed, either by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf better informed, or by a Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Authority. If a private perſons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>miſinformation,</hi> could render a ſentence void, what ſentence would hold? might not every Plaintif or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant who is caſt, always pretend <hi>miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> and would not this be to place every private perſon above the Judge?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>May one be Judge in his own cauſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>In ſome Caſes he not only may be, but muſt be Judge, and to deny it is to Authorize all Rebellion. Has not the King right to judge in points concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Prerogative, and to ſuppreſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? to pretend he cannot, is it not to place another judge over the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prem? You will ſay the judge is a part; he is ſo; but head, and governs the whole. Were it not to unchair the Pope to ſay he cannot be Judge in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals, becauſe a part? he is a part, but the ruling part; he is the head of the Church, and as ſuch ought to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Conſult the Canon, and Civil Law,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38071:29"/> and you will find they both defeat that pretence. For the cauſe of the Church or the ſtate, wherein the Epiſcopal or Royal Authority is concerned, is not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a private or perſonal cauſe of the man who is Biſhop or King, and for that reaſon, doth not ground an excluſion of that ſame man to judge in it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>You having premiſed what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and evidently true, and what it behooves ſecular Princes to maintain as well as the Pope; I pray come to the Popes Breves condemning the Oath, how many are they, and of what nature?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They are four; Three of <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, and one of Urban the eighth, <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth given in the year 1606 ſets down the Oath word by word; and, having taken notice of ſeveral other things in the act enjoyning the Oath, condemns the Oath as containing things <hi>contrary to faith;</hi> which Breve, directed to the Engliſh Catholicks, was delivered to Mr. <hi>Blackwel</hi> then Arch-Prieſt; who, notwithſtanding his inclination to the contrary, accepted it, and divulged it; by which it became ſo publick, that K. James himſelf owned it to be the Popes, and as ſuch inſerted it word by word in his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38071:30"/> anſwer to it, ſo that it could not be doubted whether it were the Popes or no. Learned men in <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> employed their pens in the defence of it. The year after, it being preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Breve was ſurreptitious and he mis-informed, the Pope in a ſecond Breve condemns it again after <hi>long and ſerious deliberation,</hi> and being perfectly informed as he declares and <hi>ex certa ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> This alſo though with the ſame unwillingneſs was publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well;</hi> but he being depoſed for taking the Oath and Mr. George <hi>Birket</hi> made Arch-Prieſt in his place, <hi>Birket</hi> publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them abſolutely, as did alſo Doctor Worthington, Aſſiſtant of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt; as alſo a third of <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth recalling the faculties of ſuch, as held or abetted the Oath. Preſtons books in favour of the Oath, Printed the one 1611. the other 1613. were by the ſame Pope condemned 1614. for all theſe Breves there wanted not ſome, as the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton and others, animated by that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Arch-Biſhop Abbot in the Clink. <hi>(See Ruſhworth Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Anno</hi> 1626. <hi>pag.</hi> 241, 242.) Who writ for the Oath, which forced Urban the 8. to give out
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38071:30"/> another Breve in condemnation of the Oath, and confirmation of his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours Breves, which was publiſhed by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Smith. Could more be done by the Sea Apoſtolick to require a due obedience?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Notwithſtanding all you have ſaid, the Oath teaches flatly deny the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of theſe Breves.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Their denyal muſt be made out; the contrary being clear by Originals, it being a Maxim in Law, <hi>preſumitur fact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quod debuit fieri. What ought to be done is to be preſumed done.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>It is ſaid the Pope was <hi>mis-inform'd;</hi> and it is prov'd thus, the word <hi>murthering,</hi> in the Latin verſion of the Oath preſented to the Pope, is Tranſlated <hi>occidere to kill.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>And what then? the Engliſhing out of Scripture the word <hi>non occides, thou ſhalt not murther,</hi> is it to misinform the people of Gods command? why then the Latining the word to <hi>murther, occidere,</hi> mis-informs his Holineſs; can any one think the word, <hi>occidere,</hi> applyed to the ſacred perſons of Kings, can ſignify Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medley; if not, it implyes an <hi>unlawful killing;</hi> which is <hi>murthering:</hi> and do not the Oath-Teachers themſelves, term the Doctrine of <hi>murthering, King-killing Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine?</hi>
                           <pb n="54" facs="tcp:38071:31"/> and ſurely they will grant, <hi>occide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> ſignifies to kill. Another objection is that the Popes firſt Breve, on which the others are grounded runs thus. <hi>Que cum ita ſint, ſatis vobis ex ipſis verbis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectum eſſe debet, quod hujuſmodi juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſalva fide Catholica, &amp; ſalute animarum vestrarum praeſtari non poteſt, cum multa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineat quae fidei &amp; ſaluti aperte adverſantur.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Pray Engliſh theſe words.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>The Pope having ſet down the words of the Oath, ſays, <hi>which things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo: out of the words themſelves, it muſt be well enough known to you, that this Oath without prejudice of Catholick faith, and ſalvation of your ſouls cannot be taken, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it contains many things, which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly repugnant to faith and ſalvation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>What is there in all this to except againſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>It ſeems not to be true, that the Oath, <hi>contains many things, which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly repugnant to faith and ſalvation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The Pope ſays it is true, that the Oath <hi>contains many things contrary to faith;</hi> the Oath-Teachers ſay, it is not true; Is not this as good as to Challenge the Pope, who is Judge, to make good his words? can a petty Lawyers ill ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38071:31"/> opinion free me from the obedience due to the Judges ſentence? is it not againſt faith for a ſecular Proteſtant pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to place it ſelf in the Chair of the Church, to decide ſpiritual points? Is it not againſt faith to comply with that power, much more to ſwear that power to be a lawful one? Is it not againſt faith to ſwear a thing to be Heretical, which is not? Is it not repugnant to faith, to diſcover all <hi>Prieſts</hi> comprehended under the common ſenſe of the word <hi>Treaſon?</hi> So that were we not obliged to ſubmit to the Pope as Judge, doth not reaſon compel us?</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>BUt if after all this, I think the Oath to be Lawful, may not I take it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No, Becauſe ſuch a thought can not be well grounded, for it neither hath Authority nor Reaſon to rely upon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>How ſhall I know that my thought is well grounded?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>By examining whether it be not a raſh one, proceeding from engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, paſſion, or in conſideration of what
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38071:32"/> is ſaid to the contrary, and by diſcuſſing the certainty of the thing I ſwear unto. For, if I have not a Moral certainty of what I am to ſwear, I cannot rationally apply God's veracity to the affirming of what I doubt of.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray you deſcend to a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, can I ſwear Innocent the 11. is Pope?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes: becauſe I have a moral cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of it; as I have of my King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But he may chance not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and ſo be no Pope. Conſidering the natural cauſes, there is a poſſibility of it, but the pure poſſibility of a thing affords me no ground to think it is or it is not: and therefore weakens not the certainty I have that it is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Have not the Jeſuits in France ſubſcribed to the like Oath?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>Never; and had the ſixteen who ſubſcribed ſome other propoſitions done it, what would it have ſignify'd againſt the judges ſentence? Would it not be pleaſant for one caſt in Chancery, or an other Court, to get the opinion of ſome Lawyer againſt the judges ſentence, and ſo think to carry it?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38071:32"/>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Did not the Jeſuits ſubſcribe that the <hi>Doctrine of depoſing was wicked, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>They ſubſcribed to the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Santarellus, whoſe book contain'd more then that. But grant they did, did they ſwear to what they ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed? and is not more certainty requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to an Oath, then to a ſubſcription? and could a ſubſcription of ſixteen Jeſuits make it <hi>Heretical?</hi> It is not enough for a private ſpirit to ſubſcribe that it is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God</hi> to make it <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical:</hi> but the Church muſt define it to be contrary to the word of God, which it never yet has done.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>Is not the French Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance the ſame with the Engliſh?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>No, as will appear by the French Oath turned into Engliſh. But firſt you know full well, that in the year 1615 the third ſtate of France, in which the Hugonot party was very ſtrong, propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Oath, much like to our Engliſh Oath of <hi>Allegiance.</hi> But what was the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue? the other two chief ſtates, the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> rejected it as <hi>pernicious, cauſe of Schiſm, and the open gate to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy:</hi> as you may read in King James his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38071:33"/> Preface to his declaration for the right of Kings, ſet forth in French in the ſame year, and in the Eloquent Oration of Cardinal Peron, made in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the third ſtate, in the name of all the Nobility and Clergy of France, and afterwards ſent to our Soveraign King James: in which Oration the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal affirms that the third ſtate enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Oath, had their Leſſon given them from England.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>I pray you give me the French Oath in Engliſh, for I perceive what ever was acted in France, as to the depoſing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, haply concluded in it. And the Oath-Teachers uſed to ſay it was the ſame with the Engliſh.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The Oath runs thus. I ſwear on the moſt holy and ſacred name of God, and promiſe to your Majeſty, that I ſhall be as long as I live, a faithful Subject and ſervant, and ſhall procure unto you all ſervice and good to your Kingdom, as much as I am able, that I never will be preſent in any Council or enterpriſe to the prejudice of the ſame; and that, if any thing come to my knowledge of this kind, I will make it known to your Majeſty, and ſo help me God and his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38071:33"/> holy Goſpel. An Oath of this Tenour none can refuſe to his Majeſty, and we are all bound to take it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But one requeſt more I have to make you; how comes it to paſs that the Pope's Declaration binds to a complyance in not taking the Oath, even with the loſs of Liberty, Life, and Fortunes, ſeeing the precepts of the Church do not oblige with ſo much Rigour?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>The Caſe is clear, it is becauſe the Law of God obliges me not to take an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Oath, and the Law of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable: now the Pope in the preſent Caſe, as being Gods Vicar acts the part of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and declares my obligation of not taking the Oath to be a part of God's Law: from which it follows, it is indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable. On the contrary, the Precepts of the Church are diſpenſable by the power that Enacted them, and oblige not to ſo much inconveniency, as the forfeiture of Lives and Fortunes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <p>But have not the Errours of other Popes been preſſed upon you, as of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas, John, Caeleſtin, Alezander,</hi> &amp;c. And that neither <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, nor <hi>Urban</hi> the Eighth is more Infallible than they; and that if the Breves of others may paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſerved, ſo may theirs.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:38071:34"/>
                        <speaker>S.</speaker>
                        <p>And have not I remitted the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that Objection, for the Anſwer to <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> from whom he Engliſhed it? They ſpoke as private men their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exacted no Obedience, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were not obeyed. Let him produce a Precedent in the Church if he can, of Obedience denyed to two Popes, iſſuing no leſs than 4 Breves upon the ſame point, and exacting a Compliance under Eternal Damnation. This is the preſent caſe, but no more; there is no dealing with private Spirits expreſſed in their Words, <hi>If I know what I know better than the Pope can tell me, I'le believe my ſelf.</hi> The Will Rules; Reaſon hath little place. I conclude, humbly begging my Reader to peruſe, more than once, this Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then to judge who of the two are better grounded in Principles of Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Government, and Religion; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers, or the teachers of the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
                        <p>The Oath-teachers, delude their King and Magiſtrates; for <hi>Firſt,</hi> they declare they only ſwear their Opinion, and their changeable Opinion can be no Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. <hi>2ly.</hi> they only ſwear againſt the Popes ſpiritual Authority of Depoſing,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38071:34"/> and not his Temporal annexed to it; nor of any other Prince. <hi>3ly.</hi> Where they ſwear they deteſt the Doctrin of Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or Murdering, as Impious and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, they mean only Similitude, and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude including diſtinction, they make it neither to be Heretical nor Impious. Though the Doctrin of Murdering be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely both Impious and Heretical. <hi>4ly.</hi> They Swear to diſcover all Treaſons, that ſhall come to their knowledg; but they do not mean all Treaſons, declared by Law ſo to be, nor the knowledge had by Confeſſion. <hi>5ly.</hi> When they ſay they ſwear without any Reſervation whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they except the forementioned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions. Laſtly, when they Swear the Pope cannot Authoriſe any Forreign Prince to invade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They do not mean he cannot implore their Armies, and perſwade them to Invade in caſe of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
                        <p>What then doth this Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to, as they ſwear it?</p>
                        <p>The Refuſers of the Oath, are ready to ſwear his Majeſty to be their lawful King, and by conſequence all due <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him; they are ready to ſwear they will never Teach or follow the Doctrin of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38071:35"/> they are ready to ſwear they will diſcover what ever Conſpiracy againſt his Majeſty, that comes to their knowledge; in a word, they are ready to ſwear the ſtricteſt Oath, that ever was yet tendered by Catholick King to his Subjects.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:38071:35"/>
                  <head>The Appendix.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>WHat if the Pope ſhould command you to ſwear the Depoſing Doctrine to be an Article of Faith, and the Oath to be Lawful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay he is not to be obeyed; he being ſubordinate to God, who forbids me to ſwear without the requiſites to a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oath; and, in this Caſe, I ſhould be as far from the requiſit of certainty of what I were commanded to ſwear, as I am certain, that Doctrine is no Article of Faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>In that Caſe the Pope would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it is an Article of Faith, who are we to believe, the Pope or God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <p>This his declaration would be as void as the Parliament's is in declaring it is <hi>Heretical:</hi> it being a certainty that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38071:36"/> it is neither <hi>Heretical,</hi> nor an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſeem then to deny that the Pope can declare the Depoſing Doctrin to be an Article of Faith; whereas in a Controverſy whether it be or no, it belongs to the Pope to decide it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <p>Where there is a Controverſy in a Point that is meerly Spiritual, I ſay, I am to ſtand to the Pope's Deciſion; but as to the point of Depoſing, it is neither meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual, nor in Controverſy, it being certain, it is no Article of Faith: againſt which certainty the Pope cannot declare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray explain your ſelf a little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <p>The Point in Controverſy between Pope and King, is not whether the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Depoſing be <hi>Heretical,</hi> or an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith.</hi> For it is certain, it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for where the Conteſt on both ſides is Lawful, neither the one can be an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> nor the other <hi>Heretical,</hi> as is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38071:36"/> manifeſt; the controverſie between them is this. The Doctrine of depoſing, grounds a Title or Right to depoſe Kings in caſe of Hereſy and revolt from the Church.</p>
                     <p>The Doctrine of not-depoſing, grounds an oppoſite right; both theſe rights are Temporalities, as is clear; the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy is, which of the two Pretenders to Right, hath Right of his ſide, Pope or King;</p>
                     <p>I ſay, they are both Parties, both Supreme Judges, neither can decide: it belongs to the whole Church, if to any, to do it; and till that be done, each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may oblige their ſubjects in Temporals to ſtand for their Right, but cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to ſwear as a certainty the Doctrine on which it is grounded either to be <hi>Heretical,</hi> or an Article of Faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M.</speaker>
                     <p>But ſhould an Oath be tendered, either for the depoſing Doctrine it's being <hi>Heretical,</hi> or an Article of Faith: to whom would it belong to judge of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, or Unlawfulneſs of it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:38071:37"/>
                     <speaker>S.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, it is already judged of by Gods Law, as it is that I cannot ſwear white is black; to declare it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful belongs to the Spiritual Court; an Oath being an Act of Religion, if true; a Sacriledge, if falſe; nor doth ſuch a Judgment incroach upon the right of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their Party, neither Party having right to a falſe Oath; and, though the Pope as to the Right of depoſing, be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to the Point of the Unlawfulneſs of the Oath, he is Judge.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:38071:37"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>The Catechiſt Catechiz'd:</hi> OR, LOYALTY ASSERTED.</p>
                  <p>In a LETTER to A Father of the Society; IN Anſwer to a Catechiſm wrirten by One of his Order, againſt the <hi>OATH</hi> of <hi>ALLEGIANCE,</hi> ENTITULED, <hi>A Brief Inſtruction touching the Oath of Allegiance, by way of a Dialogue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1681.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:38071:38"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:38071:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Catechiſt Catechiz'd:</hi> OR, LOYALTY ASSERTED, IN A Letter to a Father of the Society, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Father,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Aſſembly of your fathers in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> &amp; their <hi>Negotiation</hi> there in the month of <hi>April,</hi> 1678. wrought as different impreſſions in the minds of men, as was their affection or diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards them. The Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks thought them innocent, others believed them Criminal; ſome faulted their ill Principles, but clear'd them from the ill Effects with which they ſtood charged; But all men admired (in that period) the great Juſtice and Wiſdom of God, who, to put an Everlaſting Curſe upon depoſing and murthering Doctrine, was pleaſed to let paſs a ſeverity upon ſome deſcendents from thoſe Anceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, who by advancing unwarrantable Doctrines, had wrought amongſt us the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38071:39"/> diſturbance both of Church and State; for this was but an Effect of the ſowre Grapes their Fathers had eaten.</p>
                  <p>At their next aſſembly Triennial, which was at <hi>Ghent</hi> in the month of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> 1681, the world was big with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſome publick Act or deed, whereby their whole Province ſhould renounce and diſown thoſe fatal Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; the ſmart of which themſelves, and others for their ſakes, had ſo lately felt; and long ſince the whole Maſs of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks from the moſt Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Powder-Plot to this day. This 'twas thought by many would be the only Salve to all our Soar's, would ſweeten the Temper of the Government now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated, and ſet them, and all of us right in the opinion of all good men. But, alas! all our hopes are faded; for not only before this laſt Aſſembly both Manuſcript and printed Libels were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed amongſt their Confidents, againſt the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> but even then, by common vote of the Conſult a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory Decree was made againſt it; antecedent to which an Invective by way of a Catechiſm was ſet forth with an artifice fit to impoſe upon the weak and illiterate.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:38071:39"/>
                  <p> The firſt care of the Catechiſt is to rack the words of the Oath, ſtretching them beyond all ſenſe or reaſon, ſo to raiſe a ſtorm of ſcruples in the minds of his readers, and caſt a miſt to offuſcate the cleareſt light imaginable. What can be more clear or Tranſparent to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Capacity than the Exordium of this Oath? and what can be more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily wreſted and diſtorted from it's plain and common ſenſe then it is by this Catechiſt? Take an Eſſay. The Oath begins thus, <hi>I A. B. do truly and ſincerely acknowledge, profeſs, testify and declare in my Conſcience before God and the World that our Soveraign Lord the King is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and rightful King of this Realm, and of all other his Majeſty's Dominions and Countries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Would you imagin he could ſtick at this? yet ſo it is, and the ſcruple is, that by theſe words the King's right in lieu of being aſſerted is brought into Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (certainly either he or the Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers were ſtrangely out; for, doubtleſs their deſign was to put it out of all Queſtion) the reaſon given is, <hi>becauſe</hi> ſayes he, <hi>To teſtify and declare, as distinct from the other words, is to bear Witneſs,</hi>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:38071:40"/> 
                     <hi>and as it were to act the part of a Judge in clearing a thing not ſo well known; and is it not to question the right of a King to call the Subject and ſwear him a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it?</hi> Reverend Father, I now give you only a Taſt of his ſcruples, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both this and the reſt with their anſwers, until I meet them in their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and therefore at preſent ſhall only put this queſtion to you, whether in reaſon the Oath ought to be refuſed for ſuch wretched Conſtructions as this is? and what Oath can be deviſed, againſt which a Thouſand ſuch exceptions may not be urg'd?</p>
                  <p>His next concern is to fix in the mind of his Diſciples a Character of his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; but, in Terms ſo General, ſo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocal, that the Oath he offers to ſwear by may be taken, the King may be depoſed and murthered by the ſwearer, and yet no man perjured. His words are buſhes in which lurks the Fox of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; let's beat a buſh and try if we can unkennel him. In the end of his book, <hi>The refuſers,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of the Oath are ready to ſwear his Majeſty to be their Lawful King.</hi> Very well; but how long ſhall he be their Lawful King? a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38071:40"/> longer then the Pope will allow him to be ſo? Clearly no; For, ſince they refuſe to renounce and abjure his depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power, he is but a precarious King; the Pope may depoſe him, (as he has attempted upon others) he may abſolve his Subjects from their <hi>Allegiance</hi> engaged to him by this Cobweb Oath; nay, he may by his Breves or Bulls Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his Subjects in Caſe they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere to obey him; (for this is no new thing in the World) and he may alſo declare all this to proceed from his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Power, of which the Pope (if we may credit this Catechiſt) is ſole Judge, from whom there is no appeal, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from his Nineth Chapter. Is not this to Equivocate and ſport with the Crowns and lives of Princes? He proceeds in his Mock-Oath thus: <hi>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers are ready to ſwear they will never teach or follow the Doctrine of depoſing.</hi> What in the name of Wonder is this? will they abjure the depoſing Doctrine? No; will they hold againſt it without an Oath? No: will they ſwear to ſtand by the King and diſobey the Pope in caſe he ſhould by his Breves or Bulls
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38071:41"/> declare that as Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt he abſolves the Subjects from their <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and Excommunicates all thoſe who obey the King? No; For this diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Popes Breves they have Cenſured in others, and in his Nineth Chapter he declares the Pope to be the Sole and Infallible Judge in the Caſe. What then muſt be the import of theſe ſlippery words, <hi>they will never teach or follow the Doctrine of depoſing?</hi> or what advantage comes to the King by them? But admit the ſenſe be that they ſwear to ſtand by the King notwithſtanding any Papal depoſition, though they will not abjure his Power; Is it honour or Conſcience to ſwear to diſobey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Judge whom they hold <hi>with certainty to be infallible?</hi> Can his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty repoſe any truſt in them? or can he believe any Oaths binding enough to thoſe who maintain ſuch Doctrines? To hold the Pope Infallible, and at the ſame time to ſwear to diſobey his Bulls of depoſition, deſerves neither credit from Pope nor King.</p>
                  <p>The laſt Article of his new Oath is, that, <hi>they are ready to ſwear</hi> that they <hi>will diſcover whatever Conſpiracy againſt</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38071:41"/> 
                     <hi>his Majeſty.</hi> So far 'tis well; but, when the Pope ſhall Depoſe his Majeſty, then he will be no more his Majeſty; and ſo the King will find himſelf deluded by this Oath. And, what if after this the Pope ſhall prohibit this Oath, by his Breve, to be taken by Roman-Catholicks? as undoubtedly he may, and will; for, as the Power of Depoſing is Abjur'd by our Oath of Allegiance, ſo is the Exerciſe of that Power renounced by this new Oath; and aſſuredly the Pope will be as tenacious of the Exerciſe of his Power, as of the Power it ſelf; this being vain and uſeleſs without that. Is the Pope, in this caſe of Prohibition to be Obeyed? If ſo, adieu all Allegiance promiſed by Oath: Is he to be diſobey'd, then the <hi>9th.</hi> or laſt Chapter of his Catechiſm will riſe in judgment againſt him, it being a Self-Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>Reverend Father, you have here the deſign of the Catechiſm; whoſe Doctrin, though it be but the ſame boil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Capon often diſht and ſerv'd up (Objections ten times Anſwered without a ſtep advanc'd) yet becauſe it is now haſht and minced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Catechiſm, ſo to allure weaker Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, I ſhall adviſe them of the Poiſon it brings, and apply the Antidote.</p>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:38071:42"/>
                     <head>The Preface to the Reader Examined.</head>
                     <p>AS the Preface to his Catechiſm is Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partite, ſo ſhall be my Anſwer. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He declares againſt <hi>Perjury,</hi> with which he couples the Oath of Allegiance; ſo, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Communion Falſhood with Truth, Light with Darkneſs, Chriſt with Belia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Divers,</hi> ſays he, <hi>by taking an unlawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Oath have encreaſed the Evil of Perjury.</hi> If ſo, then 'tis to be hoped that divers who have taken a lawful Oath have decreaſed the Evil of Perjury; and ſince the Oath of Allegiance may be ſuch (for any thing oppoſed by him) I know not why it may not work a perfect Cure to that Evil, in the Sphear of Loyalty; whereas an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating Oath (ſuch as he now offers) is ſo far from Curing that preſently it Kills <hi>Perjury,</hi> 'tis Confeſſed, is the worſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sins, and Equivocation in an Oath is the worſt of <hi>Perjuries.</hi> Barefac'd perjury i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſoon diſcovered, and the Author ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhamed into Repentance; but perjury in Maſquerade, or Equivocation, lies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; and, when diſcloſed, it ſtands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it's terms of Juſtification, and has eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a Colour for the miſchief it does, which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38071:42"/> renders it Incurable. He that by Oath Equivocates with his King, can never be true to his God. And ſince your <hi>Antifimbria</hi> gives a Challenge to him who preſumes to ſay, that any of your Society holds the Doctrin of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, ſince it was very lately Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by his favour, is, That if <hi>Antifimbria</hi> be the Catechiſt, and the Catechiſt be of your Society, <hi>Antifimbria</hi> is the man, and the Oath he offers to take, is my Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
                     <p>From hence I ſtep to the ſecond part of his Preface, wherein he diſcloſes a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. <hi>Some</hi> ſayes he, <hi>who took this Oath, have ſince ſlept at a Miniſter's Sermon, and took the Cheering Cup; others have renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Popes Supremacy, and the greateſt part, abuſed by the ſpecious Title of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſwore what they meant and meant what was juſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is a Hodg-podg of good and bad together, all put to the account of the Oath of Allegiance; whoſe hard Fate it is, that for it's ſake, even what is beſt in an Oath muſt be hated; for, what can be more Rational in a Man than in due Circumſtances to <hi>Swear what he means,</hi>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:38071:43"/> 
                        <hi>and mean what is juſt.</hi> For, if he ſwears otherwiſe than what he means, he muſt either Lye, or, to give it a finer Term, muſt Equivocate. But he add's thus, <hi>their meaning was far from the words they ſwear.</hi> Was it ſo? Then clearly they did not ſwear what they meant; which can only be when their words and their meaning go together. And, if any who have taken this Oath have renounced the Popes Supremacy, I hope it was in Temporals; and that's the very Life and Soul of the Oath of Allegiance. But, if the Abjuration was of purely Spirituals, it can no more be charged upon this Oath than upon the Oath or Vow made in Baptiſm. Nor is the deſerting Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Roman-Catholick-Church, <hi>or taking the Cheering Cup,</hi> as he calls it, in the Proteſtant Church, or any other by aſſing from the Roman Catholick-Faith, neer ſo much the Effect of this Oath as the diſorders of Private Members of his or any other Religious Family is to be imputed to the vow of blind Obedience to their General, ſince the Oath is no Cauſe of them.</p>
                     <p>In the third part of his Preface he ſeems to have a priviledge to ſay any thing; and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38071:43"/> therefore impoſes upon the defenders of the Oath, as their Doctrin, that <hi>they ſwear not to the words as they lye, but only their Opinion;</hi> and yet, whoever amongſt the approvers of the Oath of Allegiance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelf with the bare thought or only Opinion of the Truth of it? How often have they declar'd <hi>That a Rational ſettled Judgment or imoral Certainty,</hi> and ſuch as is required in all Oaths to juſtify a prudent and Conſcientious Man, (though poſſibly the thing ſworn may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) is requiſit to take this Oath? Has he ſo ſoon forgot the Leſſon I read him out of the moſt Eminent of his Four and Twenty Elders in <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> when he had cenſured them and all others as diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, who were not of his mind? Is his new Oath with which he profeſſeth to Live and Dy, more binding than this? Will he diſobey the Pope in caſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares this new Oath to contain many things repugnant to Faith or Salvation? If not, his Allegiance will certainly Dy with him, but he'l not Dy with his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance. If he diſobey the Pope, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this Evidence againſt his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, that he is obliged to burn his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and ſo ſhall neither by it convince
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38071:44"/> his Adverſaries nor confirm his Friends, much leſs reclaim others, which is his deſign.</p>
                     <p>The Account of his Preface is thus. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he makes this Deduction, ſome have of late been Perjur'd, <hi>Ergo,</hi> a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and good Oath ought not to be taken. <hi>Secondly,</hi> things unconnected and diſparate he makes to be Cauſe and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> what is moſt perfect in an Oath is by him reputed Vicious. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> he Impoſes upon the defenders of the Oath Opinion in lieu of Certainty as a requiſit to an Oath; <hi>Laſtly,</hi> he prefers an Equivocating Oath to an Oath that is Clear and Candid. Reverend Father, is this Chriſtian Doctrin? Now before I take his Catechiſm in Peeces, I ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you a few Notes, ſhort, clear, and eaſy, the Obſervation of which alone is a ful vindication of the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and a Total Defeat to his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</p>
                     <p>My firſt Note ſhall be, that, ſince our underſtandings are ſo fruitful and various in their Productions, and our words ſo few that they cannot adequate every di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Notion of the Mind, it muſt ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably follow that many words muſt be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38071:44"/> Equivocal, that is, muſt contain many different meanings, from whence muſt riſe great Obſcurities in ſpeech and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; for the clearing of which a regard muſt be had to Circumſtances, as time, place, perſon, antecedents, conſequents, the end and motive of ſpeech, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All or ſome of which do uſually give light to the Auditor or Reader, and fix words to a determinate ſenſe; if therefore in the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> there be any word in it ſelf Obſcure or Equivocal, and if it be circumſtanc't by theſe or ſome of theſe advantages, 'tis render'd unequivocal and clear.</p>
                     <p>My ſecond Note is, that, as in all Arts the ſignification of Terms is borrowed from the Maſters of thoſe Arts, ſo is it in the art of Equivocating or other Dodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſpeech; the Teachers of which, as they have delivered us theſe following Terms, <hi>Equivocation, Mental Reſervation, Material prolocution, and Mental Evaſion:</hi> ſo have they given us the ſenſe of them. Equivocation is when a word of it's ſelf capable of many Senſes is by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances fixed to one only, in which the Auditor underſtands it, but the ſpeaker craftily means another; for example, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38071:45"/> to journey I deſire my friend to buy me a Horſe; he promiſes me ſo to do, meaning a painted Horſe; this is Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; for, though the word <hi>Horſe</hi> may ſignify a Real or Painted Horſe, yet in theſe Circumſtances it can only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Real Horſe: Secret or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Reſervation is, when part of a ſenſe is exteriouſly pronounced by words, and another part which ſhould make out the whole ſenſe is interiourly hid or reſerved in the mind of the ſpeaker, ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon his Auditor; as if, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogated, whether I did ſee <hi>Peter</hi> to day? I ſhould reply (having notwithſtanding ſeen him) <hi>No,</hi> reſerving in my thoughts, <hi>not in the Church.</hi> Material prolocution is a pronouncing of words parrat-wiſe without any meaning. Mental Evaſion is a general expreſſion and common to all theſe Cheats by words. Now as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocation, ceaſes to be in words, when all Circumſtances concurr to give them a determinate ſenſe, ſo it fares with men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or ſecret reſervation, when what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would be hid and reſerved in the mind is laid open by declarative Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; for then nothing is conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and what is not concealed is not mentally or ſecretly reſerv'd.</p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:38071:45"/>
                     <p> My third note ſhall be, that this Term <hi>Heretical</hi> is Equivocal in it ſelf as having divers plain and common ſignifications; for, ſince Uſe and Cuſtom is the Rule of ſpeech, conſonant to which this word <hi>Heretical</hi> imports Oppoſition, ſometimes to the word of God written (in which ſenſe 'tis always uſed by Proteſtants,) ſometimes to univerſal Tradition, and ſometimes, to the definitions of General Councils, or to ſome Conſequence deriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from any of theſe, clearly there is not any one of theſe Oppoſitions but what is the plain and common ſenſe of the word <hi>Heretical;</hi> hence it is that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that there were Antipodes, was anciently by ſome cenſured for <hi>Heretical,</hi> as by others the ſtanding of the Sun and rouling of the Earth has lately been. Hence the Divines in the Schools do day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Object Hereſie to each other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out refuſing communion with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and upon any one of theſe Methods the <hi>Cenſores Librorum</hi> and Biſhops at their Tribunals have proceeded to the cenſure, <hi>Heretical.</hi> If then in the Oath of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> there be Circumſtances reſtraining it to any of theſe notions. Evidently that muſt be the plain and common ſenſe of the word.</p>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:38071:46"/>
                     <p> My laſt note is, that Popes, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo holy and learned may in their private Letters or Breves, nay and in their Bulls too, proceed from miſinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from others, as alſo upon their own private opinion, and by ſo doing may Err to the great prejudice of others; in which caſe there muſt be a Rule by which the errour may be diſcovered; and if it prove fatal to Church or State, the Pope is not to be obey'd. Theſe notes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, I ſhall apply them to particulars as my Method ſhall direct me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>His firſt and Second Chapters Examined.</head>
                     <p>IN the firſt two Chapters he ſtates the Queſtion, whether the Oath of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> be Lawful or no? then ſums up the requiſits to a Lawful Oath, as that it muſt have <hi>Truth, Lawfulneſs of the thing ſworn, and a neceſſity to ſwear.</hi> Then, to make ſure work of it, 'tis reſolv'd the Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> ſhall fail in all, and ſo fairly concludes it every way unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. The proofs of his bold aſſertion are ranged in his following Chapters, through which I ſhall attend his march. But,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38071:46"/> firſt, I ſhall ſmooth a Rubb or two which in theſe two Chapters he thought fit to put in my way. The firſt is, that the Title of <hi>Allegiance</hi> does ill become this Oath; and his reaſon is, <hi>becauſe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part, is meerly ſpeculative and aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and therefore no Oath of Allegiance.</hi> So that in his Opinion the Title ſquares only to the promiſory part, which he tells you <hi>is in order to bind our ſelves to another, but an aſſertory Oath is a ſwearing in order to be believed.</hi> I beſeech him in his next Catechiſm to declare what it is in the Oath he calls meerly ſpeculative? Is the Kings right to the Crown there aſſerted a meer ſpeculation? Fare-well then King, whom this Catechiſt has ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred only King of Fairies, and whoſe Kingdom at this rate, is but a Fools Paradiſe. Otherwiſe I ſhould think that every Subject that by Oath aſſerts the right of his Prince, and abjures the Pope's and Subject's Power to depoſe or murther him, were by vertue of this Oath (though no promiſory Oath ſhould follow) to defend his Prince, and oppoſe the Pope and rebells. The right of a Prince and the duty of a Subject are Correlatives, they live and expire toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38071:47"/> no man can aſſert the one, but muſt aſſert the other: if ſo, 'tis clear the aſſertory part of the Oath is not meerly ſpeculative, or in <hi>order only to be believed,</hi> but alſo tends to practiſe. Again, is not the aſſertory part of the Oath as much the duty of a Subject as the promiſory? Will the King take it well or think him worthy of truſt who by an Oath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to obey and defend him, whoſe right to command he refuſeth to aſſert? Evidently then the aſſertory part of the Oath is as much the Duty, Fidelity, or <hi>Allegiance</hi> of the Subjects towards their King as the promiſory; it being the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom upon which the promiſory part is grounded; and therefore who ſticks to own the Kings right to command, is as unfaithful to him as he who denies him a promiſe to obey. I conclude then, that not only the promiſory but alſo the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertory part of the Oath makes up the Oath of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond <hi>remora</hi> he puts in my way is, to impoſe upon the defenders of the Oath, that they content themſelves with a bare probability of the truth they ſwear; when 'tis manifeſt they never bate an Ace of a moral certainty: though the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38071:47"/> Men of his School, as <hi>Valentia, Eſcobar,</hi> and others have advanced this Doctrine he now lays to the charge of others. <hi>Eſcobar moral. theol. Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>Exam.</hi> 3. cap. 3. <hi>Valentia</hi> and others in the places formerly cited by me. And, whereas he objects, that Illiterate perſons under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the words, nor have any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral certainty of the truth of the <hi>Oath,</hi> I muſt diſſent from him, and do believe they have as great certainty that the King holds not his Crown from the Pope, that he is Supreme in all Temporals, that as ſuch, he is to be obeyed, that no man may rob him or murther him, that his Subjects are bound to defend him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Conſpirators; and that all this is the indiſpenſable Law of God, as any of your learned School-Men, though they cannot put their diſcourſe into the right figure and mood.</p>
                     <p>Let us now account for theſe two Chapters, Firſt to aſſert the Kings right, and to renounce all power of the Pope and Subject to depoſe or murther him, is deny'd by him to be a part of the Subjects due <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the King. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he impoſes the Doctrine of ſome of his own School upon others againſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38071:48"/> their expreſs declaration to the contrary. Laſtly, he concludes the generality of men uncapable to underſtand, that rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and murthering, is againſt the Law of God. Reverend Father, is this Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrine?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>His tbird Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>THis Chapter begins with reciproca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the old ſaw; And ſince he will neither give any reaſon why my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to his thred-bare objection does not ſatisfy, nor can improve it any farther, my anſwer is ſtill in force againſt him. The objection was, and now is, from the Title of the Statute wherein the <hi>Oath</hi> is contained, which runs thus, <hi>An Act for the diſcovering and ſuppreſſing Popiſh Recuſants;</hi> and, as if the Title could not be verifi'd by other parts of the Statutes, or as if all parts of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute muſt be in the Title, he inferrs from thence, that the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> was deſigned to diſtinguiſh betwixt Papiſts and Proteſtants, not betwixt Loyal and diſloyal Papiſts; though the Law-maker for whoſe ſafety, and by whom the <hi>Oath</hi> was made into a Law, both in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38071:48"/> and Apology to Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; the Law it ſelf, declares againſt him. So that in his judgment, to take the <hi>Oath</hi> is in the eye of the Law, to be a Proteſtant, to refuſe it a Papiſts; and ſo by the Title of the Law a Quaker is rendred a Papiſt.</p>
                     <p>Reverend Father, to rid my hands for ever of this ſo often repeated objection, pray obſerve that I voluntarily and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without any force from his way of arguing, have and do give him his objection. What then? ought not the <hi>Oath</hi> be taken by a Papiſt? Abſur'd! For, put caſe that the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (being perſwaded that the Papiſts commit Idolatry) ſhould oblige their Subjects by an <hi>Oath</hi> to renounce Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, would not the refuſal of this <hi>Oath</hi> (with the ſame Juſtice) by the deſign of the Law diſtinguiſh betwixt Papiſts and Proteſtants. And muſt a Papiſt therefore refuſe this Oath? Nay, ought he not to take it the ſooner, ſo to undeceive the world, and unmake the Sign? This is our caſe: Some eminent perſons of your Society aſſerted at that time the depoſing and King-killing Doctrin; the Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-plot-men put it into Practiſe, amongſt whom ſome of your Society were
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38071:49"/> charged with it, and executed for it. The King and Parliament, ſuppoſing it (as well they might) to be the Doctrine of our Church, fram'd an Oath to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure it; This Oath now by Law, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to many a diſtinctive ſign betwixt Proteſtants and Papiſts; what then muſt a Papiſt do who abhors that Doctrin? Clearly, he ought to abjure it, ſo to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive the People, and unmake the ſign. From hence I conclude, that the Objection from the Title of the Statute is diſpatch'd.</p>
                     <p>But, if he will not accept of my deed of Gift, then I reſume my Liberty to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from him; and I have for my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence King <hi>James,</hi> who beſt underſtood the Deſign of his own Law, and aſſures all Chriſtian Princes, that <hi>The Oath was made for a true Diſtinction, not betwixt</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts <hi>and</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>but betwixt</hi> Papiſts <hi>of quiet Diſpoſition, and in all other things good Subjects; and ſuch other</hi> Papiſts <hi>as in their Hearts maintained the like violent bloody Maximes as the Powder Traitors did.</hi> Prem. pag. 9. and in his Apology: and this he writ at that time, when both the Title and the Statute was in the Eye and Mouth of every Man: Wherefore nothing but the Defence of a bad Cauſe could force this <hi>Catechist</hi> to Derogate from the Credit,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38071:49"/> Truth, and Honour of this Prince, whoſe Teſtimony the Statute it ſelf does Ratify, declaring that the Oath was framed, <hi>For the better Trial how his Majeſties Subjects stood affected in point of Loyalty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Now had the Oath been deviſed for diſtinction in Religion, probably the words would have been thus, <hi>For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Trial how his Majesties Subjects stood affected in point of Religion.</hi> To that of King <hi>James,</hi> no reply with Juſtice can ever be made; but to the Statute he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers thus, That ſuch a preamble is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe prefixed <hi>To the Ordaining the taking of the Communion in the Protestant way.</hi> And yet it is no diſtinctive ſign betwixt loyal and diſloyal <hi>Catholicks,</hi> but betwixt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Catholicks.</hi> I reply, That the Receiving the Communion in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> way, is in it ſelf Eſſentially a ſign of <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> but to Renounce by Oath the depoſing or murthering Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to declare it to be againſt the Word of God, is no Eſſential ſign of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> but only of Loyalty; Conſequently, whatever the Preamble be, the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> is a ſign of Loyalty, and receiving communion in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant way is a ſign of Profeſſion of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:38071:50"/>
                     <p> The Expences of his Third Chapter are thus. <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is a Repetition of the ſame Objection ten times anſwered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Improvement. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He gives his Adverſary advantage againſt himſelf. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He expects that the Title of the Statute, ſhould be as large as the Statute. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To compaſs his Deſign, he confounds the Nature or Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of things. Reverend Father, is this Chriſtian Dictrine?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>His Fourth Chapter examined.</head>
                     <p>IN this Chapter he begins to take the Oath aſunder, and divides it into two parts; the one Aſſertory, and the other Promiſſory; and againſt each part moves many vain and impertinent Scruples. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing he meets with is a Giant, but of his own creation. His firſt encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is againſt the Aſſertory part, which once more he degrades from ſharing in any part of Allegiance, becauſe <hi>it is not a promiſe of Fidelity, therefore it is no Oath of Allegiance.</hi> As if it were not as much a duty of a Subject, to maintain by Oath the Right of his Prince, upon which all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Fidelity muſt be built, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38071:50"/> it ſelf. Since therefore both parts are a performance of the Subject's duty, both parts do integrate and compleat the Oath of Allegiance.</p>
                     <p>Before he advances farther, he thought it expedient to expoſe to view theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of the Oath, <hi>And all theſe things I do plainly and ſincerely acknowledge and ſwear, according to the expreſs words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain and common ſenſe and understanding of the ſame words, without any Equivocation or mental Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation whatſoever.</hi> This is a ſnare in which he hopes to catch the ſwearer tripping by perjury, as acting contrary to his <hi>Oath.</hi> His firſt Gim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crack is from the firſt words of the <hi>Oath</hi> thus, <hi>I A. B. do truly and ſincerely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, profeſs, teſtify and declare in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God, and the world, that our Soveraign Lord King Charles is Lawful and Rightful King of this Realm, and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Majeſty's Dominions and Countries.</hi> Who would have thought that any good Subject ſhould have ſtumbled at this? Is it an imputation to the <hi>Oath</hi> that 'tis too clear? What plain-meaning man is there who underſtood not theſe words, till now he meets with this following
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38071:51"/> croſs and crabbed Comment? <hi>To teſtify</hi> (he tells you) <hi>as importing ſomething di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, from my acknowledging, in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the expreſs words is to bear Witneſs: to declare, as diſtinct, from profeſſing, is as it were to act the part of a judge in clearing a thing not ſo well known.</hi> Surely this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm runs the fate of many Comments which is to be more obſcure than the Text. For, what exigence is there that theſe four words, <hi>I acknowledg, profeſs, teſtify, &amp; declare,</hi> muſt have all diſtinct meanings? Is it from the nature of the Law, or Oath? Evidently no. For, ſince 'tis the deſign of the Law-maker, by the uſe of words, to be clear and eaſy; and ſince nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces more to that deſign than ſynoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous words giving light to each other (for ſome of neceſſity will be more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure than others) 'twould be prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to expect from the nature of an Oath or Law a diſtinct Sence for every word: Nay, 'tis againſt all Experience, for both in the Canon and Civil Law, in Statutes, in Bonds, in Indentures, in Deeds, and in the Breves, and Bulls of Popes, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo frequent as redundance of words in the ſame Sence; and all little enough to render the Acts or Obligations clear, ſure and binding.</p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:38071:51"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why muſt the words of this Oath be uſed in the moſt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſence? methinks the plain and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence (required by the Oath) ſhould not be always the moſt rigorous ſence. And I am very certain that, if all words were uſed in their rigorous ſence, few would underſtand them, and ſo they would be unfit for Oaths. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> what warrant has he, that theſe words <hi>Teſtify and declare in my Conſcience</hi> do import in rigour, <hi>to bear Witneſs before a Judge,</hi> and <hi>to act as it were the part of a Judge?</hi> Since nothing is more familiar in plain and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sence, than to Teſtify and declare a matter in a man's Conſcience without the thought of any act of Juriſdiction. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To teſtify and declare in a man's conſcience, that the King is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, is ſo far from queſtioning the Kings right, that it places it beyond all queſtion. For, whereas at the time this <hi>Oath</hi> was framed, and before, ſeveral Divines of the Society and others, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the depoſing and murthering Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which gave riſe to the Powder-Plot; this Oath was made, wherein theſe words, amongſt others, were induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inſerted, to cut off all ſuch preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38071:52"/> Power. So that what queſtion was about the Kings right, was ſtarted by the men of depoſing and murthering Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, againſt whom, and their Doctrine, this Oath was made.</p>
                     <p>Another Bone too hard for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, is that he cannot Swear, <hi>The King is Rightful and Lawful King of all his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</hi> Becauſe he knows not what they are, or what Right the King has to them. My Anſwer is, That the Oath requires not that the ſwearer ſhould know every ſpot of Land poſſeſſed by the King, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Europe, Affrica,</hi> or <hi>America;</hi> but only that he ſwear in particular, That he is Rightful and Lawful King of this his Realm, and (in general) of all other his Dominions. So that what ever change has been made of his Dominions ſince the framing of this Oath, either by gain or by loſs to the Crown; nothing is more certain, than that he is lawful King of all his Dominions; we may therefore with all ſecurity in Conſcience conclude, that in the firſt Clauſe of this Oath, there is neither Equivocation, ſecret Reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mental Evaſion, or any juſt cauſe to aſperſe this Oath?</p>
                     <p>His Bill of Charges runs thus. Firſt,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38071:52"/> he denies it to be part of the Subjects <hi>Allegiance</hi> or Fidelity, to aſſert the right of his Prince. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in defiance of reaſon, and his own experience he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in an Oath, that every word have a diſtinct ſenſe from others. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> he confounds the plain and common ſenſe of words, obvious to every underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with their rigorous ſenſe, known to a few only. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> he forces the words, <hi>teſtify and declare,</hi> from their plain and common ſenſe, that he may fault the Oath. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> to declare the King's right, ſo, that no body can juſtly take it from him, he tells you, is to queſtion the Kings Right. <hi>Finally,</hi> he has a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſwear the King is Lawful King of his Dominions; as if Dominion could be his, and not his. Reverend Father, is this Chriſtian Doctrine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>His Fifth Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>THe deſign of this Chapter, is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the takers of the Oath perjur'd, as uſing ſecret reſervations inconſiſtent with the Oath, obliging them, <hi>to the plain and common underſtanding of the ſame words</hi>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:38071:53"/> 
                        <hi>without Equivocation, mental Evaſion, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Reſervation.</hi> His firſt charge of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, is from the third Clauſe or branch of the Oath, which (if you credit him) is thus, <hi>I declare in my conſcience before God, that the Pope, neither of himſelf, nor by any other means, with any other, can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King.</hi> Had he been a fair dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, he would have cited the words as they are in the Oath thus: <hi>nor by any other meanes with any other, hath any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Authority to depoſe the King.</hi> Which differs from this other expreſſion, <hi>can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King.</hi> For Authority in the Oath, coming after Power, does limit it to a juſt and Lawful Power; whereas <hi>can depoſe,</hi> implies a power either juſt or unjuſt to depoſe the King, and the Oath meddles not with an unjuſt power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him; but, becauſe it is a Maxime in the Law, <hi>id ſolum poſſum quod licite poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> I will ſuppoſe he meant well. What does he inferr from thoſe words? <hi>that neither the Pope, nor King, nor Prince, nor Emperour,</hi> hath any power or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to depoſe the King? To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him out of his own Inſtruction, that by theſe words of the Oath, nothing is deſigned but an Excluſion of the Popes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38071:53"/> Spiritual power to depoſe the King. He reſumes thus, <hi>do the expreſs words of the Oath bear this reſervation?</hi> I anſwer, here is no Reſervation, but the plain and common ſenſe of the words, as they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by all man-kind; for, when menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made of the Pope's Power of depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Soveraign Princes, who ever under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands any other, but ſuch as Popes have claimed; and what Pope ever laid claim to the depoſing power, or procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the depoſition of Soveraigns, but by vertue of a Commiſſion from Jeſus Chriſt, as being Vicar and Supreme Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor upon earth? <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh was the firſt, that made uſe of that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; ſeveral others have followed his ſteps: examin their pretences, turn over their Bulls and publick Declarations, and ſee if they plead not a Commiſſion from Chriſt, as being Supreme Paſtors. This is the ſenſe of <hi>Bellarmin, Suarez, Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana, Becanus, Heſſius, Leſſius, Tolet, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia, Gretſer, Hereau,</hi> and all thoſe of the Society, who with ſo much heat have advanced the Popes depoſing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. In fine, this is known, and common, even <hi>Lippis &amp; tonſoribus;</hi> ſo that, though the power of depoſing be in it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38071:54"/> ſelf Equivocal, and may imply a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual or Temporal power, yet, when 'tis attributed to the Pope, 'tis then fixed to a Spiritual power, and is ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by all.</p>
                     <p>He ſtill purſues me thus, that by this Oath, 'tis not only ſworn <hi>that the Pope, neither of himſelf, nor by any Authority of the Church, or See of Rome, has any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depoſe the King; but alſo that the Pope by no other means, with any other, has power or Authority to depoſe the King; which implyes that no body can depoſe the King; not a Pope, nor King, nor Emperour.</hi> I anſwer that, if this be his conſequence, he muſt needs have a very hard opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both the Framers and Takers of the Oath; the one for forcing men to ſwear againſt a Noon-day light, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and the others for ſo ſwearing. But to defeat this conſequent, no more is requiſit than to look upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which is, <hi>that the Pope by no other means, with any other has power or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to depoſe the King.</hi> So that ſtill 'tis the Popes Power or Authority, which is only renounced by this Oath, not any other. For thoſe words can only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that the Pope, what ever means,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38071:54"/> he makes uſe of, though, he has the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or the great <hi>Mogul</hi> on his ſide to aid him, has no Power or Authority to depoſe the King. And this is truth; though it may be, the Pope alone is ſtronger than the King, and can bring more forces into the field. By this you ſee what little care he has in deriving his conſequences; which, though feeble, he leaves to ſhift for themſelves.</p>
                     <p>Poſſibly he may advance farther, and make this Objection. May not the Pope, being a powerful Prince, and injur'd by the King, right himſelf by force of Arms: and, ſo, if victory be of his ſide, diſpoſſeſs the King of his Dominions? Undoubtedly he may; but not by that Power and Authority, which is renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Oath, as is evident from the common notion all men have of Power and Authority to depoſe, when placed in the Pope. And therefore, when it ſhall happen that the Pope does war with the King, or other Princes, if he be ſtronger than they, he may diſpoſſeſs them, as they may him; but then this is not done by what we call Papal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Authority, but by natural ſtrength and Reaſon; and, in ſuch caſes, we muſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38071:55"/> uſe the ſame Terms, as cuſtom gives to other Princes, when they are Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as that they <hi>have conquered or ſubdued ſuch</hi> a Prince or King; it not being ſo uſual to ſay, they have depoſed ſuch a Prince; and when the word <hi>depoſing</hi> is apply'd to the Power of a Temporal Prince, all men underſtand it to be a Temporal Power; but, when 'tis ſpoken of the Pope, no man thinks upon any other, than his Spiritual Power as Chriſt's Vicar. When therefore the Pope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers by his Temporal Sword, the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances he is in declare to the world in what ſenſe the word <hi>depoſing Power</hi> is uſed. From hence I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that from the common uſe or plain ſenſe of the word <hi>depoſing</hi> (when joyn'd, to the Pope's power without other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) is meant only his Spiritual Power, and that without any Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſecret Reſervation; for, where nothing is conceal'd or hid, nothing is reſerv'd.</p>
                     <p>The next clauſe he jumps upon is this, <hi>I do believe in my conſcience, and am reſolv'd, that neither the Pope nor any perſon whatſoever, hath power to abſolve me from this Oath.</hi> This clauſe he tells you
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38071:55"/> is no more true, than the former, and I am much of his mind. The reaſon he gives is, <hi>becauſe the King by quitting his Crown may quit me of my Allegiancc.</hi> Beſides, <hi>the power of Victory transfers Allegiance from one King to another.</hi> This branch, I confeſs, has not much of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in it, but is full of ſolid Truth. For, although the power of Victory may transfer <hi>Allegiance</hi> from one Prince to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and the King by quitting his Crown, quits me of my Allegiance, yet that's not done by any Abſolution; for <hi>Abſolution</hi> or <hi>abſolving from Oaths,</hi> are by uſe and cuſtom, Terms appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Acts of Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, as is likewiſe <hi>abſolution from ſin;</hi> and, in this ſenſe were always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in this Oath; this being the common notion of the words without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Equivocation or ſecret Reſervation. And, truly, if the Tranſlation of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from Prince to Prince, or from King to his Succeſſor by a voluntary gift may be termed <hi>Abſolution from the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> with as much juſtice a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince, may be ſaid to abſolve his Subjects from their Oath, by Transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Allegiance to his Succeſſor,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38071:56"/> which was by Oath obliged to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour; for, though by death the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be taken from the dignity which is continued in the Succeſſour, yet in his ſenſe of <hi>Abſolution,</hi> the Subject is as truly <hi>abſolved</hi> or quit of his Oath of Allegiance given to the predeceſſour, as he ſhould have been if reſignation had been made to the Succeſſour before death. To allude therefore to the lameneſs of his diſcourſe, I introduced him in the laſt anſwer I made to this Objection, putting this queſtion: <hi>What if the King ſhould dye, is not the Subject</hi> quit of his Allegiance? Shewing by the folly of that queſtion, how far he prevaricated from the true ſenſe of the Oath.</p>
                     <p>But after all this pother about nothing, let us put the caſe, that not only the power of depoſing in general, but even when 'tis appropriated to the Pope in particular, as alſo the power of abſolving, were Terms Equivocal or imply'd a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Reſervation, is it not in the ſphear of Concomitant Circumſtances to clear them from that ſtate, and fix them to a manifeſt Certainty? Thus then I diſcourſe; the deſign of this Oath, was the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the King, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38071:56"/> from the pretended Spiritual Power of the Pope in depoſing Princes, and abſolving their Subjects from their Allegiance. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Oath was thought upon) was made an Example of that Power; for though he was not actually depoſed, yet the Pope had declared him depoſed, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects abſolved from their Allegiance, and all perſons Excommunicated who ſhould obey him. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had her ſhare in ſome ſad effects of this Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Power. Upon pretence of this Power it was that the moſt deteſtable Powder plot was laid, to have deſtroyed King <hi>James</hi> and all the Royal Family in the great Aſſembly of the Kingdom; for whoſe ſafety and defence againſt this Power the Oath was made. <hi>Bellarmin, Suarez,</hi> and others of that School main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that Power by their Pens. King <hi>James</hi> and others (his Subiects) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome were Roman-Catholicks, vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly oppoſed them. From hence 'tis evidently concluded, that the Power of Depoſing and Abſolving from the Oath, muſt be underſtood of Spiritual Power in the Pope or Church, and that no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Reſervation intervenes, ſince nothing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38071:57"/> is concealed which by clear and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able circumſtances, is not revealed. So ends this Chapter.</p>
                     <p>The ſumme of his gains in this fifth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is this; <hi>Firſt,</hi> he corrupts the words of the Oath. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he will have words to ſignify without rule, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of words he has no regard to <hi>ſubjecta materia,</hi> or the matter in hand. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> by vertue of his Logick, he can make one to be two, or two to be one. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> he minds no Circumſtances in the underſtanding of words. <hi>Finally,</hi> to beat down the Oath, he forces the word <hi>Abſolve</hi> out of his proper, to an improper ſence. Reverend Father, is this Chriſtian Doctrin?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>The Sixth Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>THis Chapter ſpeaks loud, promiſeth much and performs little; a deep mouth is a ſign of ſlow heels; for the game which he thought was in his hand, is beyond his reach. Three things he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts in this Chapter. Firſt, <hi>to juſtify the Popes Breves:</hi> Secondly, <hi>to ſtop the mouth of his Adverſary:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>to clear himſelf of his Loyalty.</hi> God ſend him a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38071:57"/> good Deliverance. The method to his deſign is to charge the fifth branch of the Oath with a ſmall parcel of Hereſies or Articles repugnant to Faith, in number no more than five. The Pope, though he declares in his Breve, that there are many things againſt Faith in the Oath, yet in his wiſdom thought it fit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal them; nay, being from time to time with humble ſupplication ſollicited to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them, would never condeſcend to any diſcovery. How came the myſtery to be now reveal'd? Is this Catechiſt the Pope's Nuncio, has he any warrant from him to define what is Hereſy? If not, he is deeply guilty of uſurping a power of defining, no more appertaining to him, than to the King and Parliament, againſt whom he is ſo earneſt for uſing their judgment only of diſcretion in Cenſuring a propoſition for <hi>Heretical.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Clauſe of the Oath which he now attacks runs thus. <hi>And I do farther ſwear, that I do from my heart abhor, deteſt, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure, as Impious and Heretical this Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctrin and Poſition, that Princes which be excommunicated or deprived by the Pope, may be Depoſed or Murthered by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or any whatſoever.</hi> Before I enquire
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38071:58"/> into the Hereſies with which he chargeth this Clauſe. I have two exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; the <hi>first</hi> is, that he permits ſo many ſynominous expreſſions to paſs uncontrouled in this Clauſe, for which he ſo hotly inveighed againſt the <hi>firſt:</hi> For <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Poſition, abhor</hi> and <hi>deteſt, to ſwear againſt,</hi> and <hi>abjure,</hi> ſeem to march in ſynonymous couples. My ſecond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception is, that he paſſeth by this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>as Impious,</hi> tacitly allowing the Doctrin abjur'd to be Impious, though not Heretical. Whereas in truth, there is the ſame rule for both; the repugnance to the Word of God giving both denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; and therefore whoever may ſwear to abhor apoſition as <hi>Impious,</hi> may abjure it <hi>as Heretical.</hi> But theſe are only points of incogitancy; his Eyes and Thoughts being fixed upon a bunch of Hereſies which hangs from this branch of the Oath.</p>
                     <p>The Firſt Article againſt Faith in this Clauſe, he declares to be, <hi>for a Secular Power, much more a Proteſtant, to uſurp the Supremacy due to the Church in deciding what is Heretical.</hi> Had he been pleaſed to have term'd it <hi>againſt good manners,</hi> for the Secular or Proteſtant Power to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38071:58"/> have gone before the Spiritual or Church, in deciding what is Heretical, it had been more moderate; but to ſay 'tis againſt Faith, 'tis unpardonable. For, what if a General Council ſhould afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine the ſame Doctrine to be Heretical, which King <hi>James</hi> and his Parliament have done in this Oath, (which for ought he knows in good time it may) would they have acted any thing againſt Faith, meerly becauſe they prevented the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil? If ſo, then all thoſe Pious Chriſtians, who declared <hi>Arianiſm, Eutychianiſm, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarianiſm,</hi> and the like, to be againſt their Faith, before the three Councils de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined the ſame, did all act againſt Faith. Nay, the hot <hi>De-fide-men</hi> of the Schools, who ſo highly value themſelves upon their Doctrine, crying out, <hi>The Church, the Church,</hi> at every turn, and knocking their Adverſaries on the head, with <hi>hoc eſt Hereticum,</hi> will not be exempt from this cenſure; ſince a thouſand propoſitions have been by them declared Heretical, never thought of by any Council. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more frequent amongſt the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Books, than ſuch Qualifications; and ſhall it be ſaid, they have all uſurp't the Supremacy of the Church in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38071:59"/> or that they have acted againſt Faith? If ſo, let them be all Hereticks for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond point he defines to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Faith in this Clauſe is, a comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in <hi>the Swearer with that Uſurped Power; it being,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>an Approbation of that Uſurpation.</hi> Is it not pleaſant, that what he has concluded againſt the Maker, and Swearer of this Clauſe, may all be true, and yet the Clauſe it ſelf be clear and innocent? So it is; for a bare Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Supremacy in declaring what is Heretical, as alſo a bare compliance with that uſurpation are the faults of the perſons, not of the Clauſe; which may be very good and orthodox whilſt the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Complyer are not. How then comes it to be concluded, that this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Faith in this Clauſe?</p>
                     <p>The third Hereſy he faſtens upon this Clauſe, is, <hi>That it makes a doctrine Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, which has never been condemn'd by the Church.</hi> I anſwer, that neither the Oath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, nor the Church her ſelf, can ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by their condemnation, a doctrine He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, which was not ſo before their Condemnation: If then the Doctrine, which by this Clauſe is declared to be
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38071:59"/> Heretical, be ſuch in its ſelf before the declaration, (as it may be, for any thing now oppoſed) how can the declaration of it in this Clauſe be againſt Faith? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, do not Catholicks as well as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants repute that to be Heretical which is repugnant to the clear Word of God? Do not the Divines in the Schools cenſure that for Heretical, which is in Oppoſition to an evident conſequence derived from Faith? And is not either of theſe the plain and common ſenſe of this word <hi>Heretical?</hi> Why then, in the acceptation of that word, muſt we be ty'd up to his humorous Notion, ſince common uſe, which gives life to words, has left us at liberty? And, ſeeing the Law-maker's Rule of Faith (in whoſe ſence we are to ſwear) is the Word of God written, if what in this Clauſe is declared to be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, be truly againſt that Rule, how is it poſſible this Clauſe ſhould be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Faith? Is not this an odd piece of Doctrine to be put into a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm?</p>
                     <p>His fourth and fifth charge againſt this clauſe of the Oath are, that <hi>it makes that to be Faith, which is not.</hi> And <hi>that to be Hereſy, which is none.</hi> But becauſe I have
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38071:60"/> onely his bare word for this Aſſertion, I ſhall only oppoſe my Negative to his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative. But the truth is, the five He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies he has charged upon this clauſe, do all center in this laſt; ſo that all five could be but one, and that's left Unprov'd; A great Cry, but no Wooll!</p>
                     <p>To ſolace Kings, and deliver them from the fears they may be in from the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Doctrine, he tells them that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Doctrine is no part of Catholick Faith: <hi>Nor doth any man,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>as a Catholick, believe it.</hi> What a rich Cordial is this to the heart of the King! But I fear it will not much pleaſe <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, or thoſe who are of opinion that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the Depoſing Doctrine is the renouncing Faith. However, the King has gained this one point of him. And 'tis hoped another may, by a little impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, be wreſted from him. For greater Security then of the King, I put this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to our Loyal Catechiſt: Is the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Doctrine no part of Jeſuitiſm? For (to ſay nothing now of the King-Killing Doctrine) did not the moſt eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the Society, as <hi>Bellarmine, Tolet, Suarez, Leſſius, Becanus, Heſſius, Mariana, Valentia, Gretſer, Hereau,</hi> and many others;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38071:60"/> and ſome of them to the Kings face aſſert the truth of this Doctrin, and even put it to the account of Catholick Faith? Again, may a man be a good Subject, and hold this Doctrin? if ſo, where's the Kings ſafety? Nay he is more expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to danger than if it were a part of Catholick Doctrin? for, in that caſe, his enemies being bare-faced and known, he could better provide againſt them; but now he knows not friend from foe. Father Whitebread your Provincial (of whom I will have the good opinion that he neither did tell a lye, nor E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocate at his death) deliver'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus at his execution; <hi>nor can any man as a Catholick believe that 'tis lawful upon any occaſion or pretence whatſoever, to deſign or contrive the death of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, or any hurt to his perſon?</hi> This is part of his laſt ſpeech, as I have in my laſt letter to you evinc'd againſt this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſt both out of the copies which were printed by Authority, and alſo out of thoſe copies ſent by your Fathers to <hi>Rouen,</hi> to be tranſlated into <hi>French,</hi> and printed there; to this I gave this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction with the Vulgar, to whom he addreſſed his ſpeech, <hi>that no Catholick can</hi>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:38071:61"/> 
                        <hi>believe it lawful to deſign the death of the King,</hi> &amp;c. Againſt this conſtruction your Catechiſt excepted in a former print, and by theſe words, <hi>no man as a Catholick can believe it lawful to deſign the death of the King,</hi> he tells us is only meant, that <hi>'tis not a part of Catholick Doctrin, to believe it lawful to deſign the death of the King,</hi> not that it is repugnant to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Doctrine. So that Father White-bread, notwithſtanding his fair ſpeech, might (upon other principles) have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in his heart that it was lawful to deſign the death of the King. Now, if this be not to Equivocate with his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors at his death, I have loſt all my ſenſes; and do appeal to the judgment of man-kind if by this he could clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of what was laid to this charge, which was his main deſign. By this you may clearly ſee what little ſecurity accrues to the King by this poſition or principle, <hi>no man as a Catholick can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it lawful to kill the King,</hi> when at the ſame time, this other poſition may be true too, <hi>any Catholick may believe it lawful to kill him.</hi> This is the deduction he makes from the laſt words of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial.</p>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:38071:61"/>
                     <p> Againſt the ſecurity, given the King by the Oath of Allegiance, he argues thus; <hi>After a man has ſworn the depoſing Doctrine to be Heretical, he may afterward find it not to be Heretical, as one may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily do; then is he free from this Oath.</hi> I ſuppoſe if this had been ſo eaſy to find, this Catechiſt and his Conſorts would not have laboured ſo many years in the inqueſt of it, to ſo little purpoſe. In the mean time we will ſtand to the Doctrine of the Oath, and (as we have juſt cauſe) believe it unchangeable. And ſo long the King may ſleep ſecurely. But what aſſurance has the King from the Linſy-Woolſy Oath of this Catechiſt, which is, <hi>that he will never hold nor teach this Doctrine of depoſing, though it be not He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical?</hi> Is not this to reckon without his hoſt? How can he ſwear this without conſulting the Pope, or his General? Has he ſo ſoon forgot the men of his order, who have taught the depoſing Doctrine, and might have continued ſo doing till this day, if a timely period had not been put to it, by a ſevere prohibition from the General? And was this prohibition any more than a poſitive order, mutable at the diſcretion of the General? And
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38071:62"/> when the intereſt of the Society may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, may not this prohibition ceaſe, and a new poſitive order be given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame precept of ſtrict obedience, to advance the depoſing doctrine? May not the Pope whom he ſtyles Judge in the caſe of all Oaths, declare this new Oath to be unlawful, it being againſt the exerciſe of his Power owned by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Predeceſſours? Will he in theſe events diſobey his General, and the Pope? If not, adieu Oath, farewell Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and good night King.</p>
                     <p>In a former diſpute with this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſt, I aſſerted the particle <hi>as</hi> in this cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>as Heretical,</hi> to import either Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity with Hereſy, or only a Similitude to Hereſy, and that both of them were the plain and common notions of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. To this he now replies, that, though the particle <hi>as</hi> may ſometimes imply Identity, and ſometimes Equality, yet in our preſent Circumſtance it can only import Identity, becauſe it then one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brings Equality, <hi>when it relates to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Subjects, which.</hi> ſayes he, <hi>is not in our caſe</hi> Then he exemplifies in this propoſition, <hi>let him be to thee as a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> where he owns that a Similitude one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38071:62"/> or Equality intervenes, becauſe the particle <hi>as</hi> relates to different Subjects. For my part looking upon the particle <hi>as</hi> in theſe two following propoſitions, <hi>let him to thee as a Heathen,</hi> and this other, <hi>let him be to thee as an Heretick, or as Heretical, or Diabolical,</hi> &amp;c. I ſee no difference in the particle <hi>as</hi> that in the firſt it ſhould import ſimilitude or Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and in the laſt Identity; For, to ſay that the particle relates to different Subjects in the one propoſition, and not in the other, is to begg the queſtion; for of this 'tis we enquire, whether the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle <hi>as</hi> ſignifies <hi>Sameneſs,</hi> or <hi>Difference</hi> in the Subjects unto which it relates.</p>
                     <p>To enlarge himſelf upon this matter, he pretends to a general rule, how to know when the particle <hi>as</hi> implies Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; which, if you will believe him, then is, when <hi>it applies an Adjective to a Subſtantive.</hi> Let's make experiment of this Rule in theſe two propoſitions, <hi>let Peter be to thee as a Heathen, and let Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be to thee as an Heretick,</hi> or <hi>as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, Diabolical,</hi> or what he pleaſes. All theſe predicates are Adjectives, which do fall upon the Subſtantive <hi>Peter.</hi> In the firſt propoſition he owns the particle <hi>as</hi>
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:38071:63"/> to imply only ſimilitude or equality, and yet the word <hi>Heathen</hi> is an adjective, as much as <hi>Heretick, Heretical,</hi> or <hi>Diabolical;</hi> for there are heathen Women, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Doctrines as well as heathen Men; clearly then the rule fails in his own example. Now, that a General Rule ſhould allow an Exception is no great wonder; but, that the Exception ſhould lye in the very example, urg'd by the propounder, is prodigiouſly abſurd.</p>
                     <p>The particle <hi>as</hi> being thus common to Similitude and Identity, he puts this queſtion to himſelf; whether in this clauſe it may be reſtrained by the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to a Similitude, and he anſwers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf negatively; becauſe, if both ſences be not ſworn to, there will be a ſecret Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation which the Oath excludes. But I muſt beg leave to diſſent from him; for, when a word may have two plain &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſignifications and no Circumſtances do biaſs it to one more than to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 'tis in the ſwearer's choice to uſe it as he pleaſes, ſo he ſwears truth in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe; nor is there in ſo doing any danger of ſecret or mental Reſervation, which then onely happens, when a part of a propoſition is pronounced by the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38071:63"/> mouth, &amp; another part is reſerved ſecretly in the mind to piece up the whole, ſo that without it the ſenſe (as intended by the ſpeaker) would not be compleat. As if, you asking me whether I did ſuch or ſuch a thing, I anſwer <hi>no,</hi> reſerving in my mind, <hi>ſo as I am obliged to tell you;</hi> this later part of the propoſition is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly reſerved, and ſo the propoſition is vicious, becauſe it is deſtructive to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society. But, in our caſe, where a word or propoſition may have two plain and common meanings, and both true, I may ſwear the one, and abſtract from or not mind the other, for I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve nothing in my mind to piece out, the ſenſe of the propoſition, ſince my meaning is what the words do plainly and exteriouſly import; and ſince both ſenſes of the propoſition are true, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports not in what ſence I took it, for either of them ſatisfies the Magiſtrate, and ſo no body is deluded.</p>
                     <p>I affirm'd it was a rule in all Laws, that if a word may have two Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereof one renders the Law Juſt, the other Unjuſt, it ought to be taken in that ſence which renders the Law Juſt. Alſo, I added that in Penal Laws, words
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38071:64"/> are to be interpreted in the moſt favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſence. To this I have his Aſſent as to other caſes, but not in this; becauſe by the words of the Oath, ſayes he, <hi>All mental Evaſions, and ſecret Reſervations,</hi> are excluded. I anſwer, out of my foreſaid Notes, that when a word is equivocal, or a ſence in a propoſition ſeems to be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'd, if circumſtances do determine it, then 'tis no more Equivocal nor the ſence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd; for, what is not conceal'd is not reſerv'd. But theſe Rules of rendering the Law juſt by a fit interpretation of words, and favourable in penalties, are circumſtances ſo known, that if any thing were otherwiſe Equivocal in this Oath or ſeem'd to be reſerv'd, they fix them to a Juſt and Favourable ſence; conſequently, as to the point of Juſtice and Favour there is nothing concealed, ſo nothing Equivocal, nothing reſerv'd. This I bring <hi>ad abundan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iam,</hi> not that there is any need of this Obſervation for any thing now oppoſed, ſince the words are left in their plain and common ſence. And, as to the word <hi>Heretical,</hi> the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the Law makers, owning the the Scripture to be their Rule of Faith, hath determined it's Sence. And, if it
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38071:64"/> had not, yet the Oath, abſtracting from materially or formally Heretical, terms of School-invention, may be taken in that Abſtraction; as I may ſwear a man is a Living Creature, though by my words 'tis not reſolv'd what living Creature he is.</p>
                     <p>Reverend Father, when you ſee a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſt advancing his own Figments in lieu of Chriſtian Doctrin, you cannot but think his caſe deſperate. In all my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with him and his Conſorts, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for the taking this Oath the ſame certainty which all mankind expect to find in all other Oaths; that is, a <hi>rational judgment</hi> or <hi>moral certainty;</hi> for, theſe are my words which he read in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter now cited; but, by his wonted Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, he conceals them to poſſeſs his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with this Errour, that I hold Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Swearer defence enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perjury, and that the Oath runs to this purpoſe, <hi>I think the Pope cannot Abſolve me, I think that Doctrin is Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. I think King</hi> Charles <hi>to be my lawful King,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas in truth there is not any thing of this ſound in all my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Upon this ſandy Foundation he builds his Caſtles. True it is I aſſerted,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38071:65"/> that a Moral Certainty was conſiſtent with an Abſolute Poſſibility of the thing being otherwiſe; and that, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the ſwearer did only aſſert the truth of the thing as it is in his Conſcience or Rational Judgment, not always as it is in it's ſelf, otherwiſe few or no Oaths would be taken; and that this Moral Certainty would render the ſwearer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in his Conſcience from all Perjury, and juſtify him before God and Man. Whereas, to ſwear poſitively what he thinks to be true, is, if not perjury, at leaſt to expoſe himſelf to it, which (though what he ſwears happens to be true) leaves a guilt upon his Conſcience, and renders him in excuſable before God and man. By this you may ſee the Impoſtor detected, and his Ignorance expoſed, in not diſtinguſhing betwixt the two Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties, Moral, and Metaphyſical, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Opinion; the firſt admitting an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute poſſibility of a thing being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than is affirm'd, the ſecond exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and the third ſtanding with an actual fear and doubt that the thing is otherwiſe. I conclude then, that he who takes this Oath, muſt not onely think, but muſt be Certain, and verily judge, that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38071:65"/> the King is <hi>Rightful and Lawful King,</hi> &amp;c. and that the depoſing or murthering Power is to be renounced as <hi>Impious and Heretical.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againſt this Concluſion, he oppoſeth his Evidence for the contradictory part; and, his reaſon is, becauſe he is certain, there is no definition of the Church to make it Heretical; and he is as certain that neither private Men, nor Uniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, can make it Heretical. I anſwer, that neither they, nor Biſhops, nor Popes, nor Councils, nor Angels, can make any Doctrin Heretical, but only the Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it has to the Word of God. Again, I anſwer, that to diſobey my Prince in Temporals, is as Oppoſit to the Word of God, and alſo to the Doctrin of the Church, as 'tis to diſobey the Pope in Spirituals; if therefore it be Heretical to teach it Lawful to diſobey the Pope, 'tis full as Heretical to teach it lawful to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey the King. And, if it be Heretical to teach it lawful to diſobey him, 'tis equally Heretical to affirm it lawful to depoſe him, which I think is the worſt kind of Diſobedience. Finally, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready evinc'd, that a Doctrin may be Htretical before any Definition of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council.</p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:38071:66"/>
                     <p> Before the end of this Chapter, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers us to the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and bids us examin what Opinion that famous School held, as to this point, in <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth's dayes, as alſo at the Siege of <hi>Paris.</hi> I have, upon ſeveral exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, enlarged my ſelf upon this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, being forced unto it by his and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers importunity; and, ſince he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the repetition of it, I ſhall reduce into a ſummary what is more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in my Letters. Thus then; This Doctrin, within the compaſs of theſe times, was declared (to omit a ſcore of other ſevere Cenſures) <hi>to be contrary to the Word of God.</hi> And not only by the <hi>Sorbon</hi> was it thus declared, but alſo by ſeven more Univerſities, as <hi>Caen, Rhemes, Tholouſe, Poictiers, Valence, Bourdeaux,</hi> and <hi>Burges,</hi> and all this in the year 1626. This Doctrine, as being <hi>againſt the Word of God,</hi> was cenſured by the faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> in <hi>Bellarmin, Suarez, Becanus,</hi> and <hi>Santarellus;</hi> whereupon, by order of Parliament, ſome of their Books were burnt. And this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo Cenſured by the <hi>Sorbon, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Word of God,</hi> the moſt eminent of the Society in <hi>France,</hi> did ſolemnly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage by a promiſe ſigned under their
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38071:66"/> hands, dated <hi>March</hi> 16. 1626. to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; by which inſtrument alſo they faithfully promiſed <hi>never to profeſs any Opinion or Doctrine contrary to what ſhall be maintained by the aforeſaid Clergy and Univerſity of the Kingdom, or the</hi> Sorbon <hi>in this matter.</hi> Finally, by decree of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>June</hi> 27. 1614. the Fathers of the Society throughout <hi>France,</hi> were obliged, under pain of High Treaſon, to preach in their publick Sermons againſt the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power, as being repugnant to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrin, which accordingly they did. Thus in ſhort, have I given you the Tranſactions of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the affair in hand.</p>
                     <p>He interrogates thus, Did the <hi>French</hi> Jeſuits ſubſcribe to the <hi>Cenſure?</hi> I anſwer, they promiſed to ſubſcribe; if then they did not ſubſcribe, they were to blame; an honeſt man will ſtand to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Their promiſe is extant, dated <hi>March</hi> 16. 1626. He proceeds; <hi>Did they ſubſcribe the depoſing doctrine was Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal?</hi> My reply is in the Affirmative; for whoever ſubſcribes a doctrine to be <hi>againſt the Word of God,</hi> ſubſcribes it to be <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical.</hi> In the upſhot, he deſires to know, <hi>whether they ſubſcribed it any more than as</hi>
                        <pb n="126" facs="tcp:38071:67"/> 
                        <hi>their own Opinions?</hi> And I muſt declare, that I cannot reſolve him, whether they did ſubſcribe it ſo much as their own Opinion, or againſt it. However, if they ſtand to their promiſe, and ſubſcribe to the Cenſure, that being poſitive, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription muſt alſo be Poſitive; unleſs he knows of any Exception made in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</p>
                     <p>This Chapter has put him to Charges; the Summe Total is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> a diſcovery of his Ignorance in the notion of what is Heretical. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he numbers the ſame thing five times over, and knows it not, becauſe it is differently worded. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> he dreams of a Clubb of five Hereſies in one branch of the Oath, where none but himſelf can diſcover any. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> to ſwear the depoſing doctrine to be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, he fancies is no Security to the King; as if the owning his Crown to be from God is of no force. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> though the depoſing doctrine be never ſo often taught and practiſed by other Principles, yet, if it be not a part of Catholick Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, he thinks the King ſafe. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> he will not own that there is any ſecurity in the Oath of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> though the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer holds the Oath to be Indiſpenſable.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38071:67"/> 
                        <hi>Seventhly,</hi> he makes the Pope judge of the Lawfulneſs of all Oaths, and yet offers to take an Oath in defiance of the Pope. <hi>Eighthly,</hi> he gives a Rule for the particle <hi>as,</hi> and in the application contradicts himſelf. <hi>Ninethly,</hi> he underſtands not the meaning of a Secret Reſervation. <hi>Tenthly,</hi> he impoſes upon the defenders of the Oath Opinion in lieu of Moral Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty. <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> he confounds Moral with Metaphyſical Certainty. <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> he takes Councils to be Authors of our Faith. <hi>Thirteenthly,</hi> he is an ill bird, and beraies his own neſt, diſcovering the ſhame of ſome of the Society in <hi>France. Fourteenthly,</hi> he dodges about the Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>French Jeſuits,</hi> now owning, and then diſowning it. Finally, he ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to be an honeſt man, that is to ſwear to what he ſubſcribes. Reverend Father, is this Chriſtian Doctrine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>The Seventh Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>IN this Chapter a <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> is made after the former Clauſe; 'tis again ſearch'd into, and a new Evaſion brought to light. The clauſe is, <hi>I ſwear that I do</hi>
                        <pb n="128" facs="tcp:38071:68"/> 
                        <hi>from my Heart, abhor, deteſt, and abjure as Impious and Heretical, this damnable Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and Poſition, That Princes which be Excommunicated or Deprived by the Pope, may be Depoſed or Murthered by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or any whatſoever. This Propoſition,</hi> (he tells us) <hi>as being expoſed to Quibbles, is not proper to be ſworn by every Ideot.</hi> I am much of his mind. But this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition as it is expoſed in the clear Terms of the Oath, and not quibbled upon as Sophiſters, is proper enough to be ſworn, not indeed by every Ideot, ſuch as the Laws of God and Men exempt from Oaths, but by the Illiterate as well as the Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; for would he, and ſome few others, lay a ſide their learned Obſcurities, by which they deſign to darken all that comes in their way, the propoſition, as it lies, is intelligible to all thoſe whoſe Capacity does fit them for an Oath.</p>
                     <p>For the better underſtanding of the Scruple, he allows it to be Heretical to aſſert it Lawful to murther the King, but not to Depoſe. This ſuppoſed, he argues thus, <hi>I do not ſwear the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaying a Prince excommunicated may be depoſe and murthered, but may be depoſed or murthered, to be Heretical.</hi> My firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38071:68"/> ſhall be, that it is equally againſt the Law of God to aſſert, that a Prince Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated may be <hi>Depoſed,</hi> as it is to aſſert that he may be <hi>Murthered.</hi> For he who by his Command obligeth us not to murther, does equally oblige us not to Steal or Rob. Since therefore to depoſe a Prince is to rob him of his Crown, 'tis againſt the Law of God, and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, 'tis heretical to affirm it Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. He ask's, <hi>who has defin'd it?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, God in the Decalogue, in Holy Scripture, by Univerſal Tradition, 'tis written in the hearts of all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the repugnancy to any one of theſe principles renders a poſition Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical.</p>
                     <p>My ſecond reply is, that in caſe I ſhould allow him that the doctrin of depoſing were not heretical, yet the propoſition ſworn in this clauſe to be Heretical would ſtill be ſo: For, if it be Heretical to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it Lawful to murther the King, then for murther's ſake 'tis Heretical to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it Lawful to depoſe or murther him. For Example, if it be a Heretical poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſay it is Lawful to do evil, he that ſhall ſay 'tis Lawful to do good or evil, delivers a poſition heretical; for,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38071:69"/> by that poſition 'tis left to a man's choice to do either lawfully: If therefore either of the parts of that poſition be heretical, the whole muſt be ſo, becauſe <hi>bonum ex integra cauſa, malum vero ex quolibet defectu.</hi> He concludes this aſſertory part of the Oath with a Quere or two; <hi>firſt,</hi> how a man can ſwear <hi>that this Oath is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd unto him by good and lawful power?</hi> I anſwer, becauſe it is adminiſter'd unto him by his Lawful Magiſtrate impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erd by God ſo to do. <hi>Secondly,</hi> how he can ſwear by this Oath, <hi>heartily, willingly, and truly upon the Faith of a Chriſtian?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, becauſe 'tis the will of God that Subjects perform their duties to their Prince, not repiningly but cheerfully, <hi>hilarem enim datorem diligit Deus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His accounts of this Chapter are but ſhort. <hi>Firſt,</hi> he denies it to be Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal to teach it Lawful to rob or ſteal. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he weighs not the truth of this maxim, <hi>bonum ex integra cauſa, malum ex quolibet defectu. Thirdly,</hi> he wonders how a Magiſtrate can adminiſter a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Oath. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> he quarrels with Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects for ſwearing Allegiance to their Prince heartily, willingly, truly, and in the Faith of a Chriſtian. Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Is this Chriſtian Doctrin?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:38071:69"/>
                     <head>His Eight Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>THis is a Chip of the Old Block, ſtill tautologies, ſtill repetition of old ſtories. The Aſſertory part of the Oath is again excommunicated from an Oath of Allegiance, and my task is to Abſolve it. Again, then to aſſert by Oath the Kings Right, when required, and to renounce all power to depoſe or murther him, is the duty of every good Subject, and without which to promiſe Allegiance would be a vicious and an unjuſt Act. And, ſince the Oath is made out of both parts, my inference, in oppoſition to his, is, that by this Oath nothing but pure and candid Allegiance was intended by the Law-maker.</p>
                     <p>We are now arrived to the promiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the Oath, againſt which he ſeems to have only this exception, that the ſwearer by it does promiſe to diſcloſe, not only <hi>all traiterous Conſpiracies against the King,</hi> but <hi>all Treaſons.</hi> Now many moſt important points of Religion being by the Law made Treaſons (as <hi>to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Authority in the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>to be Ordained Prieſt by Authority derived</hi>
                        <pb n="132" facs="tcp:38071:70"/> 
                        <hi>from that See, and then to come and remain in the Kings Dominions, to reconcile or be reconciled to the Roman Religion,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>he cannot</hi> (ſayes this Catechiſt) <hi>make diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of theſe things without betraying his Religion, and he who will do ſo, will be a Traitor to his King.</hi> For my part I ſee no neceſſity why the ſwearer ſhould be reputed a Traitor either to the one or the other; ſince both the Law and Law-makers, as alſo practitioners in the Law, or Cuſtom (all which are the beſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the Law) do exempt him from ſuch diſcoveries; as ſhall be evinced by this following induction. The Statute wherein the Oath is contained aſſures him that the deſign in framing this Oath was, <hi>for the better tryal how his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects stood affected as to their Loyalty.</hi> The Law-maker himſelf, that King for whoſe ſafety the Oath was made, forecaſting that ſome unhappy Catechiſt would wreſt all things in the Oath to the worſt ſence, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents his Objection by declaring <hi>that nothing is by this Oath required but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that Temporal Allegiance or Civil Obedience, which all Subjects by the Law of God</hi> &amp; <hi>Nature do owe to their Lawful Princes, with promiſe to reſist and diſcloſe</hi> (pray ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38071:70"/> what) <hi>all contrary Uncivil violence.</hi> Premon. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. Now to maintain a Spiritual Authority in the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be a Roman Prieſt, to reconcile or be reconciled to the Roman-Catholick Church, are not things repugnant to that Temporal and Civil Allegiance, which all Subjects by the Law of Nature do owe to their Lawful Soveraigns: Clearly then the diſcovery of any of them comes not within the verge of this Oath: And therefore the Charge which is brought of High Treaſon againſt a Prieſt at the Bar has no connexion with the Treaſons to be diſcovered by vertue of this Oath, Roman Prieſthood being only Treaſon by a particular poſitive Law, and all the Treaſons to be revealed by this Oath, are onely ſuch as are againſt Temporal and Civil Allegiance due to all Princes by the Laws of God and Nature.</p>
                     <p>The next Expounder of the Law is Cuſtome <hi>(Optima interpres legum eſt conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo)</hi> by which all words are to be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. To Cuſtome then I appeal; and demand whether ever any Perſon of Worth and Honour amongſt Proteſtants who have taken this Oath and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Prieſts, and perſons by
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38071:71"/> them reconciled to the Roman Church, do think themſelves in Conſcience oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to diſcover them, believing them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of no other Treaſon than that of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and reconciling or being reconciled. That they do not, is more clear than Noon-day light. Nay, 'tis obſerved that none but the ſcum of people, who either out of Malice to ſome private perſon, or for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre, are Informers of this Nature; and, as ſuch, are by Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves reputed vile. And, whereas the Law has provided penalties for thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal ſuch treaſons as are againſt Natural, Temporal and Civill Allegiance, yet the bare knowledg of a Prieſt and not revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him is not puniſhed by Law.</p>
                     <p>To reinforce the Objection he argues thus. <hi>The ſignification of Words is taken from the will of men, which cannot be more clearly expreſſed than by their Laws;</hi> ſince then by the Laws theſe things above mentioned are Treaſons, and all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by this Oath are to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, it ſeems to him evident that thoſe alſo ought to be diſcovered, or a ſecret Reſervation (excluded by the Oath) muſt intervene, rendering the ſwearer perjur'd: This is the Sum of his diſcourſe. To
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38071:71"/> which I thus reply; that, though words ſignify by the will of men, and the will of men be expreſſed by their Laws, yet the words of the Law cannot alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the will of the Lawmaker unleſs veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with concomitant Circumſtances; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> if a word in a law may have divers ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it muſt be fixed to ſome one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. This being ſo, and the word <hi>Treaſon,</hi> in the Oath being by all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances (as by the words of the Statute, by the deſign of the Lawmaker interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Law, and by common uſe and practiſe of the Law) fixed to ſuch a determined ſort of Treaſon, that, and onely that, is by vertue of this Oath to be diſcovered. Nor is there room here, for any ſecret reſervation: for, theſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances laying all things open, nothing is ſecret, nothing reſerved. My concluſion of this Chapter, in oppoſition to his, ſhall be, not like him to applaud my ſelf, but to referr my Anſwer to men of impartial Judgment; to whom I preſent this following account.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, he excludes from an Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance the firſt and greateſt Duty of a Subject to his Soveraign. Secondly, he is endleſs in his repetition of the ſame
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38071:72"/> thing often anſwered, without advance. Thirdly, he is incorrigibly obſtinate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plain words of the Law, Law-maker and practiſe of the Law. Fourthly, he minds not Circumſtances to underſtand words by. Finally, he puts a Reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where nothing is reſerved. Reverend Father, Is this Chriſtian Doctrine?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>His Nineth Chapter Examined.</head>
                     <p>NOthing is more uſual with him than to reckon without his Hoſt; he is not content to ſtyle the Pope Chief Judge in Spiritualls, unleſs it be with the Luſtre of <hi>Soveraign;</hi> a Character, which, may be, the Pope himſelf will not admit, and thoſe who maintain a General Council to be above the Pope will not allow. Though he ſuppoſeth it as a known maxim. True it is, amongſt the Roman-Catholick Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the Pope is Chief Judge, but they are alſo <hi>Jure Divino</hi> Judges. So that in the Court of Judicature he is neither Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch nor Soveraign. But, ſuppoſe he were Soveraign Judge in Spirituals, as the King is in Temporalls, does it follow from hence that I muſt rather obey the Pope
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38071:72"/> by refuſing the Oath than the King by taking it? Yes, ſayes he, becauſe the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or Unlawfulneſs of an Oath, as a point of conſcience, lyes within the verge not of a Temporal, but Spiritual Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> If ſo, I believe the new Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance which he offers the King in the name of Catholicks, will end in a jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle; eſpecially he declaring with certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the Pope to be Infallible Judge: for, though it does not renounce the Pope's Power of depoſing, yet it ſtands in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of that Power, and renders it vain &amp; ridiculous, as never practicable; nay the Subject ſwears by it that he will ſtand by the King, and diſobey the Pope, if he attempts to depoſe him. And, can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of ſence perſwade himſelf that ſuch an Oath can be acceptable to the Pope who claims the depoſing power? will he ever permit ſuch an Oath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out declaring it Unlawful. And, if he ſhall declare it Unlawful and by his Breve prohibit it to be taken, muſt he not be obeyed as an Infallible Judge? By his Doctrine, 'tis Evident he ought. You ſee then, this Catechiſt by the offer of his new Oath deſigns to delude both Pope and King. But this anſwer is only <hi>ad hominem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:38071:73"/>
                     <p> My Second Anſwer more direct is, that, the King being the ſole Judge in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, 'tis preſumed he beſt knows his own Temporal Concerns, and the Extent of his Power, as the Pope does his in Spirituals; if then, in the defence of his Right in Temporals, he frames an Oath to be taken by his Subjects, and declares (as King <hi>James</hi> did) that he requires by that Oath nothing but Civil or Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Allegiance, and, if it be clear unto his Subjects that nothing is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Oath but Temporal Allegiance, my Anſwer, I ſay, is, that it is within the verge of the Temporal Power to judge of the Lawfulneſs of his own Oath; for the Lawfulneſs depending upon the good or ill deſign of the Law-maker and the words of the Oath, of which himſelf is the Interpreter, the deſign being only to contain his Subjects within the bounds of their Temporal Duty, and the words importing no other than Temporal Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, whoever wreſts his words from the deſign and ſence by him declared in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades his Right. Otherwiſe, the Pope aſſerting his own right or power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Kings, may, and will render all Oaths, repugnant to that Power, illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38071:73"/> For, 'tis but declaring them to be againſt his Spiritual Power, and all is in his own hand, and the queſtion of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing is at an End. Nay, at this rate of arguing, the Pope may hedge in all things within the Circle of his Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for, ſince there is nothing that bears not the badge of Good or Evil, Lawful or Unlawful, all things muſt be brought to the Spiritual Court; and then what need of Kings, when the Spiritual Power alone can govern the Univerſe?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Admit the Pope were Judge, as to the Legality, or Illegality of the Oath, muſt his Deciſion always prevail? what if he were impos'd upon by Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, as is the fate of all Princes more or leſs? what if he gave too much credit to ſiniſter ſuggeſtions; as that <hi>his Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in Spirituals was invaded,</hi> his power of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>his Juriſdiction of Binding and Abſolving wrested from him?</hi> Now, that he was in theſe unhappy cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, is too evident to thoſe who have peruſed the Books of the Miſ-infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers againſt the Oath, all of them uſing ſuch figg-leaf pretences.</p>
                     <p>But let us alſo allow that there was fair dealing in the Informers, may not this
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38071:74"/> Judge be too Indulgent to his own private Opinion; and ſo as to deceive himſelf and others? Undoubtedly he may; for on all ſides 'tis confeſs'd that Popes may err in their private Opinion; and as clear it is, that, the errour once diſcover'd, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can juſtifie an Obedience to ſuch a Power or Judge, when the Crowns and Lives of Princes, the Catholick Religion, and the Fortunes, Liberties and Lives of all Catholick Subjects muſt otherwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſacrifice to his Errour. To this great truth I have the Pope himſelf aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third a great and wiſe Prelat, who (as he is cited by a learned Cardinal, <hi>Franc. Zabarel. de Schiſm.)</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares thus: <hi>We are not to obey the Pope when there is a vehement preſumption, that the ſtate of the Church may be diſturbed, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchiefs like to follow. Nay, it were a Sin to Obey, becauſe every one is bound to prevent future evils.</hi> Innocent. de ſent. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comm. cap. inquiſit. But another great Cardinal warrants us, in ſuch caſes, not to obey the Pope, though he ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed even to Excommunication; ſo <hi>Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitanus</hi> Alledged by <hi>Sylvester</hi> in theſe terms; <hi>We are not,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>to obey the Pope, if it may be preſumed our obedience will</hi>
                        <pb n="141" facs="tcp:38071:74"/> 
                        <hi>trouble the ſtate of the Church, or becauſe of any future Evil or Scandal, though the Precept were under pain of Excommunication</hi> latae ſententiae. <hi>Sylveſter ex Panormitan. verbo obedientia. num.</hi> 5. Cardinal <hi>Tolet</hi> a Jeſuit avers the ſame truth. <hi>Tolet de ſept. peccat. mort. cap.</hi> 15. in a more ample manner; ſo alſo many others.</p>
                     <p>To take away the Ground upon which I now ſtand, he tells me, that <hi>'tis the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſentiment of Catholicks that the Pope is Infallible in points of Doctrine. Firſt,</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand how many Catholicks he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted upon this point wherein he is ſo poſitive? For I believe they will not ſtand to his engagement, at leaſt in ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a number. To father opinions upon <hi>all Divines, all Catholicks, the whole Church,</hi> &amp;c. are tricks now ſo common that they will take no longer. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number in the Church which defends Perſonal Infallibility, do they hold the Pope otherwiſe Infallible than defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Faith <hi>ex Cathedra?</hi> And will any man aſſert the Pope's private Letters to the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> (for ſo <hi>Eudaemon</hi> one of your Fathers terms them) to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions of Faith? If ſo, pray what point of Faith is defined by theſe Breves? can
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38071:75"/> there be a definition of Faith, and nothing defined? Again, was it ever heard, that a Definition of Faith was ſent in a Letter to a ſmall number of men, and not directed to the Whole Church? Beſides, where are all the Formalities, all the Ceremonies which the <hi>de-ſide</hi> men themſelves ſeek for for in Faith-definitions? Is not this to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Catholick Faith more abſurd than her very enemies could wiſh it?</p>
                     <p>But, for a more eaſie diſpatch of the Errour of our Catechiſt, who engages for Popes more than they will for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I ſhall ſhew you what ſence ſome of the greateſt and humbleſt of Popes had of their own frailty in being often ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by miſ-informations; upon which, by an exigent of feeble nature, they were forced to ground themſelves. <hi>Gregory,</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the great, ſeeing ſome to wonder that a Pope ſhould be by misinformation cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvented, replies thus; <hi>Why do ye won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that we are deceived being but men? Have you not obſerved that David a King who had the Spirit of Prophecy, gave an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Judgment againſt the Son of Jonathan; Who therefore will think it ſtrange that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors ſhould ſurprize us ſometimes; Us, I ſay, who are no Prophets? We are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed</hi>
                        <pb n="143" facs="tcp:38071:75"/> 
                        <hi>with affairs; and our ſpirits being diverted by ſo many things are the leſs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to any thing in particular, and ſo may be more eaſily mistaken in ſome one thing. Greg.</hi> Dialog. 1. Chap. 4. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him I offer you <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, who in his Breve or Letter to the Arch-Biſhop of Ravenna (which is now a Law in the Canon) declares thus, <hi>If it happen ſometimes that we ſend to your Fraternity ſuch Decrees as you are not ſatisfied with, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not your ſelf at it, for you may either with reverence put them in execution, or give us an account why you think you ought not. And we ſhall take it well at your hands, that you execute not any decree which might bave been procured from us, either by Surprize or Artifice.</hi> Cap. Siquando in reſcrip. Thus may you ſee theſe two great <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates</hi> confuting our little <hi>Catechiſt,</hi> by own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in their Letters or Breves, they may be Circumvented by Surprize and Artifice.</p>
                     <p>Perſonal Infallibility he confeſſes, is no Article of Faith, but I <hi>judge it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>definable.</hi> Well then, we are in a fair way of having a new Article of Faith, if the Church will rely upon his judgment. But, if I miſtake not, the Church will
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38071:76"/> have more than his pretended <hi>Certainty,</hi> which he aſſures us <hi>is very great;</hi> but, to what degree, whether of a high Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Moral, Phyſical, or Metaphyſical Evidence, he knows not: To evince this Certainty (whatever it be) he drops two or three Topicks with this enforcement; <hi>Who can think this, who can judge that, who can imagine or ſurmiſe another thing?</hi> So that, if you do but <hi>think, judge,</hi> or <hi>imagine</hi> otherwiſe, his Topicks are non-pluſt. And I cannot blame him to touch them onely gently, ſince he knew both <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Catholicks</hi> had often an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them beyond reply.</p>
                     <p>Quitting at laſt his poſt, or his pretence to perſonal infallibility, he brings into a parallell the Spiritual with the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judge thus; <hi>If the Pope may be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey'd in the point of Conſcience, why may not Secular Judges be diſobey'd in Temporalls?</hi> I anſwer, that neither of them againſt the Law of God is to be obey'd. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he would conclude, as from a max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, that a ſentence of a Judge paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Misinformation, ought to ſtand good, <hi>untill it be repealed by himſelf better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or by a Superiour.</hi> Nothing is more certain, than that every ſentence of a Judge
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38071:76"/> (be he Pope or King) which is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Law of God, is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void or null, and that without farther demur. This he tells you is a way to pervert all Judicature, <hi>and to place every private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon above the Judge.</hi> My reply ſhall be, to put him in a Circumſtance where his Superiour or General to whom he has vow'd Special Obedience, layes his Commands upon him which in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment clearly controul the Law of God; Then I ask him, What he would do in that caſe? Will he obey? 'twill be a ſin againſt his Conſcience, which dictates to him out of the Goſpel, <hi>That he must obey God rather than man.</hi> Will he diſobey? That cuts the throat of his own Argument; for then the Objection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns upon him, that this is to confound all, and <hi>place every private perſon above the Judge.</hi> What this Catechiſt will do in this caſe I cannot reſolve; but, for my part, I would do what all good men have done upon the like occaſion; that is, I would make uſe of my Reaſon which God has given me; and, if it be clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that my Superiour (be he Pope or King) commands me to ſin againſt the Law of God, I ſhould freely diſobey him;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38071:77"/> but with this ſubmiſſion, to receive what penalty he ſhall inflict upon me within his ſphere; for this the nature of all Government requires. Now, by doing this, I cannot be ſaid to judge the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of my Superiour with the judgment of Authority; but I make uſe of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Diſcretion, by which I and every man is to govern his Actions. And, if this Rule be obſerved, there can be no danger of placing a private perſon above the Judge; for he ſubmits to the puniſhment of the Judge, and onely prefers God before Man.</p>
                     <p>His next poſition is, <hi>That the Pope may judge in his own Cauſe.</hi> To this I anſwer as I did in my laſt, (though according to his cuſtome he over-leaps it) that, where there is a juſt cauſe of Diſpute, as he owns there is betwixt the Pope and all Kings in point of Depoſing, there is truly party and party; nor can either of them be Judge. For, though both of them will Judge for themſelves, becauſe neither will own that the other has a juſt cauſe to diſpute; yet, if truly there be juſt cauſe of diſpute, neither of them can be properly Judge; for, if one be Judge, the other muſt ſubmit to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and ſo can have no juſt cauſe to diſpute.</p>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:38071:77"/>
                     <p> Our former diſcourſe has been built upon the ſuppoſition that the Pope had authentickly prohibited by his Breves the Oath to be taken; ſo that what follows, as it is in the dark, ſo if it were allow'd him for true, 'twould advance nothing to his concluſion. But I cannot let paſs his Confidence, in being ſo poſitive that Mr. <hi>Blackwell</hi> publiſhed the two Breves of <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth; whereas, it is evident, both out of Mr. <hi>Blackwell's</hi> own writings, that he was ſo far from publiſhing them, that he ſeverely reprov'd Dr. <hi>Worthington</hi> for doing it without, nay, againſt his Order; without which no publication could then be Authentick; and at the ſame time he writ unto all the Clergy, the Gentry, and Nobility, animating them to take the Oath; declaring it to be a duty incumbent upon them by the Law of God. Nay, the Fathers of your Society themſelves (whoſe importunity had procured from the Pope this irregular power of an <hi>Arch-Prieſt</hi> in lieu of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> thinking to have ſerved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of him when firſt they preſented him to the Pope) have, and do lay it to his charge, that he refuſed to publiſh them. And what afterwards was done either by Mr. <hi>Birket,</hi> the next Arch-prieſt, or Biſhop
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38071:78"/> 
                        <hi>Smith,</hi> is ſo obſcure, and of ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to the main diſpute, that to redeem farther trouble of arguing it with him, I ſhall rather afford him ſome grains of allowance, and refer him to my forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, than trifle time, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which, though it be granted, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail him nothing.</p>
                     <p>Another inſtance of miſ-information I took from the word <hi>Murther'd</hi> in the Oath, which was tranſlated by the term <hi>Occidi,</hi> which is a Generical word, and may be uſed in a good or bad ſence; whereas the word <hi>Murther</hi> is alwayes the Killing a man againſt the Law of God. He anſwers, that, if this were ſo, then when the Command, <hi>non Occides,</hi> is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into this Engliſh, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill,</hi> it were to miſinform the People of God's Command. His Inference would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proper, if the Church in her Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm did not declare what ſort of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God did prohibit by his Law, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to the Magiſtrate the power of the Sword; and this Anſwer was given him before, it being an Objection I had made by way of anticipation; for there I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, that in the Decalogue the Church is not ty'd up to the plain and common
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38071:78"/> ſence of the words, as we are by the Oath. Then he asks, <hi>Whether any can think the word</hi> Occidere <hi>apply'd to the Sacred Perſons of Kings, can ſignifie Chance-medley; if not,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>it implies an Unlawful Killing.</hi> How? Is there no mean betwixt Chance-medley, and Unlawful Killing? What thinks he of Killing by the ſtroke of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? Is that either Chance-medley, or Unlawful? Again, what conceit has he of all thoſe Authors cited in my former Letters for defending the Lawfulneſs of Killing Kings in caſe of reſiſtance after depoſition? Did they not believe and maintain, that depoſition did deſecrate their perſons, and conſequently, that Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, in caſe of refuſal to be depoſed, was lawful? Did they believe it either Chance-medley, or Unlawful? Pray let him peruſe the places cited, and then give his Judgment. Since therefore words are not to be underſtood at his rate, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the plain and common ſence of the word <hi>Murther,</hi> which the Oath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires we ſhould ſtand too, is not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Occidi;</hi> conſequently the Pope was impoſed upon by the Tranſlator, &amp; the Oath forbidden is not our Oath of Allegiance.</p>
                     <p>The Pope having by his Breve decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38071:79"/> that <hi>it must be well enough known to us that the Oath without prejudice to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith and Salvation of our Souls can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken, ſince it contains many things which are manifeſtly repugnant to Faith and Salvation,</hi> from this declaration I argued thus; that, ſince we our ſelves are of all men moſt conſcious to our ſelves of what we know, or of what we are ignorant (that being a matter of fact, for the moſt part depending from our ſences, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes concealed within our own Breaſts) and, ſince it is ſo far from being well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough known to us that there is any thing in the Oath repugnant to Faith or Salvation, that neither our ſelves could ever diſcover it, nor our Adverſaries, whoſe concern it is to diſcountenance this Oath, could after ſo many years induſtry point it out, from hence I ſay I conclude that it was not the will of the Pope to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige us by his Breves to abſtain from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Oath. And from this knowledge derived from ſences and thus concealed, I aſſerted that <hi>every man knows what he knows and alſo what he knows not much better than any man, even the Pope can tell him.</hi> Upon this to render me dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpectfull to his Holyneſs he ſingles out
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38071:79"/> ſome of my words from their fellows by which they are to ſubſiſt, and then declares that I challenge the Pope to make good his words; when it is rather an humble Submiſſion, profeſſing our Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of what the Pope ſuppoſeth us to be knowing. After this, he runs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of Breath with queſtions alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy anſwered, as thus, <hi>Is not this againſt Faith, is not that ſo, is not a Third, Fourth, and Fifth thing ſo?</hi> To all which in their due places I have given my anſwer. Now to the levelling of his accounts for his <hi>Nineth</hi> Chapter.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, having declared the Pope to be the Soveraign Judge of the Lawfulneſs of an Oath, at the ſame time he offers to take an Oath in defiance of the Pope's Power. Secondly, he owns the King to be Supream Judge in Temporalls, yet will not allow him to Judge of what is Temporal in the Oath. Thirdly, he would have the Crowns of Princes, the Lives and Fortunes of Subjects to ſtand or fall from the Single and Bare Opinion of a Pope. Fourthly, he engages for the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Catholicks without their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and againſt truth. Fifthly, he holds the private Letters of a Pope directed to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:38071:80"/> a few men to be as Infallible as a Faith-definition; So that as many periods as are in the Popes Breves, or private Letters, ſo many new Articles of Faith are coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Sixthly, he is certain the Pope is Infallible, but with what Certainty he knows not. Seventhly, right or wrong, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God, or with it, a Judge, he holds, muſt be obeyed. Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is injurious to the Memory of Mr. <hi>Blackwell</hi> the Arch-Prieſt. Ninethly, he diſtinguiſheth not betwixt <hi>Killing</hi> and <hi>Murthering.</hi> Laſtly, he makes the Pope Omniſcient. Reverend Father, Is this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>His Concluſion of the Catechiſm Examined.</head>
                     <p>THis Concluſion of his Book is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the play of Blind-mans-Buff, where he ſtrikes at a venture without regard to Friend or Foe; then jumps to and fro without any thing of method. Will you have a taſt of his kindneſs to his friends? Thus then; I produced Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of the moſt conſiderable of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in all France, promiſing to the King under their hands to Subſcribe to the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38071:80"/> Cenſure of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> and <hi>never to teach againſt the Sorbon in this point.</hi> The Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is that the Doctrine of depoſing Kings <hi>is falſe, erroneous, contrary to the Word of God,</hi> &amp;c. To this Cenſure he will not own that the men of your Society ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, but onely that <hi>they ſubſcribed to the condemnation of Santarellus whoſe Book contained more than that.</hi> If then they did not ſubſcribe to the Cenſure againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Doctrin, having ſo religiouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed it to the King in their declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Sixteenth</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1626. where is Honeſty? Is not this to caſt dirt upon the faces of his own Fathers?</p>
                     <p>But grant, ſaies he, they did ſubſcribe to the Cenſure, <hi>did they ſwear to what they ſubſcribed?</hi> Again, where is old Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty? Will not a Religious honeſt man ſwear to what he will not refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe? If what he ſubſcribes to, be true, what harm is there in due Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to ſwear it? If it be not true, what honeſty can ſubſcribe to it. Is not this ſtill to beſpatter his French Fathers? He advances thus, <hi>Can the Subſcription of Sixteen Jeſuits make the Doctrine of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Heretical?</hi> I anſwer, no. But this argues that ſome Jeſuits have two Faiths
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38071:81"/> in their pockets; one for Rome, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother for Paris; they at Rome profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it <hi>to ſtand with the Word of God,</hi> and they at Paris declaring it to <hi>be againſt the Word of God;</hi> and is not this to play at Blind-mans-buff with his own Fathers?</p>
                     <p>Next, he asks whether the French Oath of Allegiance be the ſame with the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and he anſwers himſelf, <hi>no;</hi> but adds, <hi>that the Oath-teachers uſe to ſay it was the ſame.</hi> My reply is, that if he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy any ſuch Oath-teachers, he may fight againſt his own dream; for, I know of none who uſe to ſay ſo: nor do I ſee what great need there is of ſuch a Oath in <hi>France:</hi> for, thoſe men of your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety whoſe Books were burnt in <hi>Paris</hi> for teaching the depoſing Doctrin, do reſtrain the Pope's Power of depoſing to the caſes of Hereſy and Apoſtacy: Now the French Kings living in communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and fearing no danger from the depoſing Doctrin, it may be reaſon of ſtate in them not to meddle with the Pope's Power in their Oath of Allegiance. But, ſhould the French Kings recede from the Roman Communion, as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have done; or, ſhould the depoſing men
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38071:81"/> be found in a ſecret Conſpiracy againſt their Lives, as the Powder-Traitors were at Weſtminſter, who acted by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Principles, can he tell us what Oath the French King would then frame? If he cannot, let him learn from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees already made againſt that Doctrin both by that Church and State.</p>
                     <p>When I had in defence of the Oath of Allegiance, declared that a Moral Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty was a ſufficient aſſurance to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy an honeſt man in his Oath, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that there was no neceſſity that the thing ſworn ſhould be ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely true in it ſelf that it could not poſſibly be otherwiſe (for then no Oath, or at leaſt, but few could be taken) but onely that it ſhould be true to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Swearer, when I ſay, I had declared this, the Catechiſt both in his former print and alſo now, inveighs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me as encouraging the greateſt diſhoneſty imaginable; and yet, poor man, he is lap'ſt into the ſame errour, but ſees it not; for, he aſſures us, he has the ſame Certainty in ſwearing, the <hi>King to be the right and Lawful King of this Realm,</hi> as he <hi>has of Innocent the</hi> 11th. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pope</hi> (who not-withſtanding he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38071:82"/> may poſſibly be no Pope, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Baptized, Ordained, or being ſimonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Elected, &amp;c) which is not to ſwear the truth of a thing in it ſelf, but as it is in the ſwearers judgment, who has for warrant of his honeſty a moral Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, whatever the truth in it ſelf may poſſibly be. Is not this to play at blind-buff and contradict himſelf?</p>
                     <p>At the winding up of his Catechiſm, he propounds to himſelf a queſtion, of all hitherto, it may be, the moſt Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. 'Tis thus; <hi>How comes it to paſs,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>that the Pope's Declaration binds to a Compliance in not taking the Oath, even with the loſs of Liberty, Life, and Fortunes, ſeeing the Precepts of the Church do not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige with ſo much rigour? and he anſwers himſelf in the words following, becauſe</hi> ſaies he, <hi>the Law of God obliges me, not to take an Unlawful Oath, and the Law of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable. Now the Pope declares my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation of not taking the Oath to be a part of God's Law, from whence it follows that 'tis indiſpenſable: On the contrary, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Church are diſpenſable, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige not to the forfeiture of Lives, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</hi> The Queſtion put, I confeſs, is clear and eaſy, but in his anſwer he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38071:82"/> himſelf, though from both I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his ſence muſt be thus, that the Oath is not therefore indiſpenſable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is prohibited by the Pope, for that would not oblige us with the hazard of Lives and Fortunes, but becauſe it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God antecedent to the Pope's prohibition, and the Pope now as God's Vicar declares it to be ſo, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently 'tis Indiſpenſable. This, I ſay, muſt be his ſence, if he has any. For when he tells us that God obligeth us not to take an unlawful Oath, the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on returns what makes an Oath Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? If it be the Pope's prohibition onely, that's diſpenſable; if it be the Law of God, antecedent to the Pope's prohibition, 'tis therefore indiſpenſable. This being ſo, I ask whether this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition or declaration of the Pope be a definition of Faith, or no? If it be, where is the thing defined, without which 'tis impoſſible there ſhould be a Definition? Beſides, is not every man free to maintain any one clauſe or propoſition of the Oath, without doing the leaſt injury to the Popes prohibition or declaration? For, whoever affirms that the Pope's Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition falls upon any particular Clauſe, is
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38071:83"/> too raſh, as not having any warrant from the Pope for his bold Aſſertion: Since then every part of the Oath may ſeparately be maintain'd without infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pope's Prohibition, how can the Prohibition of the Oath, be a Definition of Faith? Clearly then the Pope's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration by his Breves is bottom'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own private Opinion, unto which though all <hi>due</hi> reſpect is to be pay'd, yet why it ſhould oblige the Catholicks of <hi>England</hi> with the loſs of Liberty, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and Lives, ſince he owns the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Church do not, I expect to be inſtructed by another Catechiſm: nor do I think he values his own life ſo little as to hazard it upon the private O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Pope, though never ſo Learned and Holy. But, if he will, he muſt pardon others who are not of his mind.</p>
                     <p>To convince him that ſome Breves of Popes may paſs un-obey'd, I inſtanced in <hi>Nicolas, John, Caeleſtin. Alexander,</hi> and moſt particularly in <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eight, who in his Bull againſt the French King declared himſelf <hi>not only Supream in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals, but alſo in Temporals, and that all were Hereticks who held otherwiſe.</hi> To
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38071:83"/> theſe Objections he ſends me to <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> to receive my Anſwer, and I at the ſame time ſent him and another to <hi>Withrington,</hi> and to <hi>John Barclay,</hi> Father and Son, who to a tittle have made good the Objection againſt <hi>Bellarmin.</hi> To ſay as he does, that thoſe Errours were the private Opinions of Popes, is to yield the cauſe, and own that Popes may err in their private Opinions; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that his Commands (ſuch as is the prohibition of the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance) grounded upon ſuch private O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, may be ſubject to miſinformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and errour. Nor does it import that the Command be of one or two Popes, never ſo often iterated, or that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace be of Temporal or Eternal pains; for, ſtill we are at this lock, that 'tis the private opinion of Popes; for which Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Life, and Fortunes are not to be ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Had he peruſed the Letters &amp; Decrees of Popes ſo often cancelled in the Church even by ſucceeding Popes, experience would have taught him that 'tis no new thing that the Decrees of Popes may ſpring from their private opinions and misinformation; and, when they do, are revocable either by themſelves or others,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:38071:84"/> and never to be obey'd to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Peace of the Church; and this without any diſreſpect to the Holy See. ſo thought St. <hi>Bernard</hi> (to omit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others) who gives this leſſon to our Catechiſt, <hi>that the Apoſtolick See has this for which 'tis much celebrated, that it stands not upon punctilioes of honour, but is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevailed with, to retract that which by ſurprize had been procured from it. 'Tis indeed but just that no body ſhould thrive by Injuſtice, and that eſpecially before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly See.</hi> Bernard, Epiſt. 180.</p>
                     <p>He was now come to the laſt period of his Catechiſm, when he thought it expedient to make a deeper impreſſion in the minds of his Readers of his little tricks and arts by a re-capitulation of his worthy feats. <hi>First,</hi> he places in the van a known Impoſture, ſaying, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that by the Oath <hi>onely our Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſworn,</hi> whereas we require a ſettled Judgment, and that with more Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> or many of his four and twenty Elders do think requiſit to an Oath, as was made out in the laſt. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he imputes it as a Crime to the ſwearers that they do not by their Oath exclude as well the Temporal power of the Pope,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38071:84"/> and of other Princes, as onely the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual power of the Pope; as if other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Pope as a Temporal Prince, may not right themſelves by force of arms, and invade the King's Dominions, as he may theirs in caſe' of wrong done him, and reciprocally poſſeſs themſelves of new Conqueſts? Or, as if King <hi>James</hi> and that Parliament, by whom the Oath was made a Law, were to be begged for Fools? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he deludes his reader again in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that we by the particle <hi>as</hi> in the Oath, doe onely mean Similitude: This I ſay is a deluſion; for we do not onely aſſert that this particle <hi>as</hi> joyned <hi>to Impious and Heretical,</hi> may be taken for a Similitude, but alſo for Identity; and that, in the plain and common ſence of the particle: and, moreover, that 'tis in the choice of a ſwearer to mean either Similitude or Identity. Nor is it materiall in which ſence he ſwears, provided his abhorrence or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Doctrine be the ſame in either. Fourthly, he blames the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, that engaging by Oath to diſcover all Treaſons, he omits to diſcover ſome that are ſuch by Law, as alſo Treaſons known in Confeſſion. As if an Oath were not framed of words, and words were
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:38071:85"/> not to be regulated by concomitant Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and <hi>Pro Subjecta Materia;</hi> as has been declared both by the Law and Law-maker. Fifthly, he charges the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer with this Perjury, that at the ſame time he ſwears to uſe no ſecret reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he actually has in his mind a ſecret reſervation; as if reſtriction of words known to be ſuch by common Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances were ſecret reſervations; or, as if what is not hid, but open to the whole world, were ſecretly reſerved. Finally, he faults the Oath, that by it is ſworn that the Pope cannot authorize any forraign Prince to invade the King, but not that he cannot implore his aid to invade him; as if to implore Aid and Authorize were one and the ſame thing. What remains is the modell of an Oath he would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the King, to be taken by his Subjects; the juggle of which is diſcovered in the beginning of this my Anſwer to his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm; to repeat it will be too tedious, and I am heartily weary of ſtill rowling the ſame ſtone, which his conſtant repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the ſame things has forced me upon: Wherefore, having made our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts even in the foregoing Chapters, I ſhall alſo ſtate thoſe of his concluſion
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38071:85"/> of the Catechiſm and ſo end.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> He puts three ſlurs upon his own Fathers in point of honeſty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> He obtrudes upon others his own dreams as their ſayings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He is guilty of that for which he blames his Adverſary, and ſees it not.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He confounds the Pope's private Opinion with a Faith-definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He would ſacrifice all the Catholicks of England to the Pope's pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Either he thinks the Decree of Popes muſt in no caſe be diſobeyed; or, if he thinks they may, he dares not give a rule for it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He commits three impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Finally,</hi> He underſtands not the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt Authorizing and Implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Aid, and is a great ſtranger to ſecret reſervation. Reverend Father, Is this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of his Catechiſm, Chriſtian Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? For to you and to the impartial reader, as he commends his Catechiſm, ſo ſhall I my anſwer; Peruſe it and weigh
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:38071:86"/> it: the more ſevere you are in the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, the more kind you will be to your ſelf and me; ſince Truth and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Truth is the Game we are in purſuit of.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Reverend Father,</salute>
                        <signed>Your ever Faithful, <hi>A. B.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="165" facs="tcp:38071:86"/>
                     <head>THE ANSWER To His APPENDIX.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Reverend Father,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THe Catechiſt, having printed and publiſh't his Catechiſm, he thought fit to ſend poſt after it an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix in a Manuſcript, by way, I ſuppoſe, of Refutation of it; for I never ſaw two things more at odds one with another than the Catechiſm and this Manuſcript are. For, in his <hi>Nineth</hi> Chapter of the Catechiſm, he gives out that the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſence of Catholicks is to hold the Pope to be Infallible in points of Doctrine,</hi> and he himſelf tells you he is <hi>certain the Pope is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> in deciding points of doctrine; and, though he owns that 'tis not Faith that the Pope is Infallible, yet he judges
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:38071:87"/> it <hi>defineable.</hi> Now againſt himſelf he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues thus in his manuſcript; <hi>What,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>if the Pope ſhould command a man to ſwear the depoſing Doctrine to be an Article of Faith?</hi> he anſwers himſelf thus, <hi>he ought not to be obeyed;</hi> and he gives for his reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is <hi>certain 'tis no Article of Faith.</hi> Is not this rare dodging with the King and Pope? In the Catechiſm, Chap. <hi>Nineth,</hi> he was certain the Pope was Infallible in deciding Faith, the Pope now [in the hypotheſis] has declared a point of Doctrin to be of Faith, and commands him to ſwear it to be ſo, but is not to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; nay, he aſſures you there is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the Pope's infallibility, <hi>againſt which certainty the Pope cannot declare.</hi> Is not this to make the Pope infallible and not-infallible when he pleaſes? Again, both in the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> and in the Appendix he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the Pope to be Judge as to the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or Unlawfulneſs of an Oath; This being ſo, does not the Pope (when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him to ſwear the depoſing Doctrine to be an Article of faith) by ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand declare that Oath to be Lawful for him to take? Clearly then to ſay the Pope in that caſe is not to be obey'd, is to make him judge and no judge as to the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38071:87"/> Lawfulneſs of an Oath. Finally, in his <hi>Nineth</hi> Chapter has he not declared the Pope to be <hi>Soveraign Judge in Spiritualls?</hi> If then he ſhall declare it to be an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith that by vertue of his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Power he can depoſe Kings, ought not this Catechiſt believe that power or right to be a Spiritual Right, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, obey when the Pope ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him to ſwear it? In his Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix he tells you, no; for he has a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration againſt his own Catechiſm. Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle now my riddle, what's this? Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and not infallible, a Judge and no Judge, a Soveraign and no Soveraign, how can that be? Reverend Father, Are theſe the Myſteries of Chriſtian Doctrine?</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:38071:88"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:38071:88"/>
                  <div type="decree">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE DECREE Of the <hi>FATHERS</hi> of the Society of Jeſus of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Province, At their Provincial Congregation made, againſt the</hi> Oath of Allegiance, <hi>at <hi>Ghent,</hi> the Fifth day of <hi>July,</hi> this preſent Year,</hi> 1681. <hi>WITH Some <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon it.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THat we may proceed with uniformity amongſt our ſelves in the manner of acting touching the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:38071:89"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us all profeſs that as much Obedience and Fidelity ought to be ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn and exhibited to our King from every one of us, as is wont to be ſworn and exhibited to any Princes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever from other Catholick Subjects.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Oath, as now it is, ſprinkled with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heterodor clauſes, cannot be taken, as being condemned by many Breves of Popes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If any (againſt the Decrees of Popes) have taught the foreſaid Oath to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, let him not be admitted to Abſolution, without Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Recantation, either made or ſacredly promiſed.</p>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:38071:89"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Thoſe who againſt their Conſcience have taken the Oath, let them be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Abſolution, without manifeſt ſigns of Repentance, and promiſe of Amendment for the future. But thoſe who with a good Conſcience have taken it, are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed: and if they renounce it, are to be abſolved.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Let care be taken, leſt either too much facility, or moroſity in abſolving, breed Scandal.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:38071:90"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="exceptions_against_decree">
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:38071:90"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Exceptions</hi> Againſt The foregoing DECREE.</head>
                     <p>AGainſt this Conſult, and the Decrees made by it, there are many Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt.</hi> A <hi>few</hi> men overvoting the reſt of the Conſult, and locking up, with the key of pretended Authority, the Underſtandings of the <hi>leſſer</hi> number of the Conſult, and of all thoſe who are not in the Conſult, do Tyrannize over them; and oblige them, when a queſtion is put (whether the Oath be True or Falſe, good or evil) to anſwer in the ſence of the Conſult, though their dictamen of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be againſt it. So that a Lay-Perſon who makes choice of a Confeſſor out of this Society for his Vertue and Learning, and thinks to find an Oracle in him, is gull'd. For, 'tis the Conſult
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:38071:91"/> that ſwayes, by whom this Confeſſor (though otherwiſe againſt his conſcience) muſt adviſe and act. And, therefore, when 'tis given out that all the Jeſuits are againſt the Oath of Allegiance, 'tis in truth a great cheat; for it may be more than half of them are for it, but being over-aw'd by ſuch Conſults to whom they have vowed obedience, they muſt either ſubmit, be puniſhed, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Order.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> To determin of an Oath whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be True or Falſe, Lawfull or Un-Lawful by number of votes of ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities (even in their fulleſt Aſſembly) is to throw Croſs or Pile, even or odd, in the ſearch of Truth. For, if the votes happen to be <hi>odd,</hi> then the Oath is True, or, if you will, Falſe; but, if they be <hi>even,</hi> 'tis a drawn match; and then it muſt be put to the vote again till an <hi>odd</hi> one ſtarts up, and that muſt carry it. In the framing of Laws for the well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of ſuch communities ('tis confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) the plurality or number of votes muſt prevail, becauſe thoſe Laws have all their force to bind the members of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, from the number of votes. But the Truth of an Oath or the Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:38071:91"/> it has to the Law of God, is independent from any Votes of the Communities, and is Truth it ſelf, and known by a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man, (ſuch as preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ought to be) not by a Plurality of Votes, but by the Laws of God, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by an Authority Infallible: ſo that to put Truth to the vote, and act againſt conſcience, is unexcuſable.</p>
                     <p>The firſt Article of this Decree promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth much in ſhew, but performs nothing in ſubſtance; it equivocates with the King, and in the end deludes him. For, when they offer to ſwear the ſame Allegiance to him as other Catholick Subjects do to any Princes whatſoever, either thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are in Communion with the Church of Rome, or out of it; if they are in communion with the Church of Rome, they have no reaſon to fear the Depoſing Power, ſince the men of the Depoſing School have taught it only practicable in point of Hereſie and Apoſtacy; and therefore out of ſome reaſon of ſtate, may ſafely enough omit in their Oath the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of that Power. But, if thoſe Princes be out of communion with the Church of Rome, I know not whether they have felt the ſmart of the depoſing
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:38071:92"/> Doctrine; ſure I am our Princes, as <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Eighth, Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>King James</hi> have run the riſque of it both in their Crowns and Lives; and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, their Succeſſours have reaſon to exact the renouncing of it, whilſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes may not. Beſides, if other Princes require leſs of their Subjects than they may, muſt we who are Subjects pay leſs duty to our Prince than in Juſtice he requires?</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Article is a great errour; for, after ſo many challenges, never yet could they find the leaſt poſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Catholick Faith in this Oath; and thoſe who by importunity wreſted any Decrees from the Pope, ſuggeſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him (as is manifeſt by their writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings) that his Power of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Supremacy in Spirituals was taken from him by this Oath; ſo that thoſe Breves were procured by artifice and ſurprize.</p>
                     <p>But, admit the Pope had condemned it, if that muſt deterr us from taking it, I know no Oath of Allegiance which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth either the Pope's power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, or the exerciſe of that power, but may by ſome Pope or other be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whileſt that Pope aſſerts his power
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:38071:92"/> to Depoſe. Nay, the Oath which the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> themſelves offer to take may run the ſame Fate; and ſo no Allegiance muſt be pay'd to the King but ſuch as the Pope will allow him, which may be none at all.</p>
                     <p>The third and fourth Article, are the vain Attempts of Men without Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For, to frame Decrees for binding and abſolving Sinners is the great Work of the Hierarchy of the Church; of which neither are theſe <hi>few</hi> Men of the Conſult, nor the <hi>whole Body</hi> of the Society any part.</p>
                     <p>The laſt Article of this Decree, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to too much facility or moroſity in abſolving Penitents, is ſomewhat ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dextrous, and ſeems to afford a caſe for every rich man's Conſcience. It wants an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to clear it's ſence; but, if Practice be the beſt interpreter of words, there will be found who will conſtrue it thus; If a powerful or wealthy man comes to Confeſſion, and having taken the Oath will not recant and renounce it, then to diſmiſs him without Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be eſteemed too much moro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; but, if a weak or poor man comes, then to Abſolve him without recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:38071:93"/> or renouncing it ſhall be deemed too much facility; which manner of carriage ſavours too ſtrong of <hi>Prudentia Carnis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Some of the Society have taken this way to cloud the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>We do not, ſay they, make the Pope his own judge in the caſe betwixt himſelf and the King, as to the depoſing Power, but only as to the Lawfulneſs, or Unlawfulneſs of the Oath, which being an act of Religion, 'tis his part to judge of it.</hi> This, I ſay, is a manifeſt eluſion of the Oath, and colluſion with the world. For, if the Pope owns in himſelf a right to depoſe the King, 'tis evident he may and will declare all Oaths Unlawful that ſtood in his way and are repugnant to his preſumed right; nay, he may frame an Oath, and (being the only Judge of the Lawfulneſs of his own Oath) oblige all Catholicks to ſwear that he has power to depoſe the King, which is to make him Abſolute Judge of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Power, Thus you ſee, theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſts and Framers of Decrees, give us many hollow-hearted words concerning Allegiance; which, when we come to graſp them, ſlip through our fingers, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh into Ayr and ſignify juſt nothing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentaries_on_decree">
                     <pb n="179" facs="tcp:38071:93"/>
                     <head>The Subſcription of threeſcore Doctors of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> to the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> vindicated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome frivolous Exceptions.</head>
                     <p>WHen a Man is ſeized with the itch of Cavelling, nothing can eſcape his Nails; but though his itch be incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his Nails will grow, yet they may be pared. The Doctors of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> who have Subſcribed to the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> offer'd to do it without any explanation; but, being adviſed to declare themſelves upon that part of the Oath, wherein ſome tender Conſciences ſcrupl'd, they freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omply'd, and ſign'd an Explanation, thus faithfully tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Subſcription of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> Doctors.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>VVE under written Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Doctors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>f the Sacred Faculty of</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is, <hi>do judge the Oath, as it</hi>
                           <pb n="180" facs="tcp:38071:94"/> 
                           <hi>is in the other page conceived, may with ſafety of Faith and Conſcience be taken by Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholicks; ſo that, the words</hi> Depoſed and Murthered <hi>[in the propoſition, which is of the depoſition and murther of Princes, and which is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as Heretical] be taken jointly; nay alſo, though ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately, ſo notwithſtanding that the Heretical propoſition, for as much as it aſſerts that Princes may be Depoſed, be taken materially (that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God) and formally alſo for as much as it adds that they may be Murthered.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This Declaration or Subſcription was given by threeſcore at leaſt of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Doctours, and is now the Subject of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> Long it was before theſe <hi>Cavillers</hi>
                           <pb n="181" facs="tcp:38071:94"/> would own to their friends in <hi>England</hi> that the Doctors had ſubſcribed, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this day ſome of them do out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the Sun: but whoſoever now will be any longer deceived, is infatuated. Thoſe who are conſcious to the truth of this Subſcription and cannot longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it have ſtill for refuge their little arts to elude it, which ſhall be laid open in theſe following paragraphs,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Some,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Pariſian Divines, famous as well for Piety as Learning, do make little or no account of the foreſaid Subſcription, for theſe following reaſons.</hi> Before I weigh the reaſons, 'tis expedient to clear their terms, for I ſee I have to do with men well skill'd in the equivocating craft. Firſt then, I beſeech them to declare who theſe <hi>Pariſian</hi> Divines are ſo famous for Piety and Learning; for words are no payment. Are they the Divines of the Faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> or are they the Divines of the Society of Jeſuites? for both may be <hi>Pariſian</hi> Divines, but both are not of the Faculty of <hi>Paris.</hi> If they be of the Society, 'tis well known that Books prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome of them aſſerting the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Doctrin were condemned both by the Church and State, and ordered to be burnt
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:38071:95"/> in <hi>Paris,</hi> and the whole order baniſht thence, upon that account; ſo that they are not the men to be conſulted in this caſe, the Oath being deſtructive to that Doctrin; Though, at this preſent, there is reaſon to believe that the men of that Society in <hi>France</hi> are of a different judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from their brethren elſewhere. But, if they be Divines of the Faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> what warrant is there under their hands for it? For to believe that theſe renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divines would renounce that ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and and famous Cenſure brought by the whole Univerſity againſt Depoſing Doctrin, declaring it to be <hi>new, falſe, erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, against the word of God</hi> (as they muſt do if they value not this ſubſcription) requires more than the bare words of the aſſerters. I ſhall alſo examine their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reaſons; for, although they give out that 'tis the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet I doubt not but to evince that the hands be of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The firſt reaſon is becauſe this <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription does formally contradict two Breves of</hi> Paul <hi>the fifth decreeing with deliberation that it is not Lawful for Catholicks with a ſafe Conſcience to take the foreſaid Oath, ſince it contains many tbings repugnant to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>aith,</hi> &amp;c. What likelihood is there that
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:38071:95"/> this reaſon ſhould be urged by any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>Sorbon</hi> who could not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that at the ſame time the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Sorbon</hi> declared againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Doctrin, as <hi>new, falſe, eroneous,</hi> &amp; <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God,</hi> ſome Popes had before aſſumed that Power, and did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, both by Breves and Bulls too, to put it in execution. Beſides, what is more familiar to the Sorbon than to aſſert the Doctrins of the <hi>Gallican Church,</hi> and the Authority of their Kings, againſt any Breve or Bull whatſoever! Nay, the <hi>French Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> themſelves have by long experience found it now expedient to diſobey the Popes Breves or Bulls which are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Policy of <hi>France;</hi> as is manifeſted in the caſes of father <hi>Meimbourg</hi> the <hi>French Kings</hi> hiſtorian, and the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> of <hi>Tholouſe, in</hi> point of the <hi>Regalia.</hi> To fix then this reaſon upon the Divines of <hi>Sorbon</hi> or the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is to impoſe upon them.</p>
                        <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe the Propoſition in which the whole difficulty is found, cannot be taken jointly but ſeparate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the words are, and this truth is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by the Learned Perot.</hi> I am glad to hear the whole difficulty of the Oath is reduced to one Propoſition. But, what
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:38071:96"/> will the Catechiſt ſay to this, who has found a knot in every Ruſh? Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſince the Subſcribers, who are three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore at leaſt, do aſſert, that it may be taken jointly, why muſt we paſs by them and yeeld our Aſſent to theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines in <hi>Maſcarade,</hi> or to one <hi>Perot</hi> (whom, notwithſtanding, the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſt himſelf in a former Print, owns to have altered his Opinion; if ſo, <hi>quem ſequntus es errantem, ſequere penitentem)</hi> there being no reaſon alledged in his or their Defence. But, to convince them that ſuch propoſitions may be taken jointly or ſeparately, I inſtance in this, <hi>'Tis lawful to live honeſt or steal,</hi> the ſence either may be, that 'tis lawful to do either of them, and then that propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is taken jointly, and is formally Heretical; or the ſence may be, that 'tis lawful to do ſome one of them, and then the propoſition is taken ſeparately, and is not heretical. The ſame in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion I affirm of this other propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>'Tis Lawful to Depoſe or Murther,</hi> which taken jointly, is formally Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, becauſe <hi>malum ex quolibet defectu;</hi> but taken ſeparately, is materially hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in reſpect of one part, and formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:38071:96"/> in reſpect of the other; nor, is it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient that one predicate may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly affect different Subjects, eſpecially both ſences being plain and common.</p>
                        <p>The third Reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Doctors without cauſe affirm that the adjectives, Impious and Heretical, are to be taken formally in reference to the word</hi> Murthered, <hi>and only materially in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the word</hi> Depoſed; <hi>nor can there be aſſigned any Reaſon, why they are not to be taken univocally in one and the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</hi> But, to evince that a reaſon may be aſſigned, I ſhall give him this; that, though the propoſition be but one, yet 'tis equivalently two, having two different ſubjects, which are <hi>to be Depoſed, or Murthered,</hi> and conſequently, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate may alſo be equivalently two, or diverſe in ſignification without any ſin againſt Logick.</p>
                        <p>The fourth Reaſon, is, <hi>Becauſe 'tis not undoubted that the Pope cannot depoſe Princes in ſome caſes, ſince many Popes and Divines of good note have taught the contrary; whom no body but raſhly and unskilfully may accuſe of material Hereſy.</hi> My Anſwer is, That amongſt the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Divines, even thoſe who were not required to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:38071:97"/> much more amongſt the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, 'tis certain the Pope has no power to depoſe ſoveraign Princes; nor, are they concerned what others doubt or doubt not; for, they hold not themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to doubt with others for company ſake; neither, are they eſteemed raſh or unskilfull in their Art for charging that Doctrin with material Hereſy; ſince nothing is more frequent in the Schools than to charge the opinions of others, nay, and ſometimes of Popes too, with material Hereſy; and that without breach of union, or any diſreſpect to the Holy See.</p>
                        <p>The fifth Reaſon, is, <hi>Becauſe, ſince the Subſcribers do ſay, that to depoſe is a doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine only materially Heretical, it ſeems 'tis not lawfull for Catholicks to take the Oath, becauſe it is as it were a faith-profeſſion, where every word is to be taken in its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal not material ſence, as is expreſſed in the end of this Oath.</hi> My Reply is, that, I find no ſuch expreſſion as <hi>formal,</hi> but plain and common ſence, neither in the end, nor throughout the Oath. A plain man and a formal are very different. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is only <hi>as it were a faith-profeſſion</hi> is <hi>no</hi> faith-profeſſion. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:38071:97"/> it be only a profeſſion of what is mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially Faith, what harm is it if the doctrin in contradiction to it be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cenſured as materially hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</p>
                        <p>The Sixth reaſon is, <hi>becauſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers do not permit</hi> Catholicks to ſwear, but with a condition, which neither the <hi>illiterate underſtand, nor magistrates do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of.</hi> I anſwer, that the ſwearer need not trouble his head with any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, but onely plainly and honeſtly abjures the poſition as <hi>Heretical;</hi> for whether it be either materially or formally Heretical or both (terms which are known onely to the School) ſo it be heretical, his Oath is good, and he in conſcience ſecure; nor do the ſubſcribers require that the ſwearer do underſtand all their terms of explication. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing Divines have declared depoſing and murthering to be againſt the Word of God, this both the Litterate and Illiterate underſtand to be heretical, and ſeek no farther.</p>
                        <p>The Seventh reaſon <hi>is, becauſe 'tis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest that all the Six profeſſors of Sorbon with many other moſt learned Divines, and all the regulars almoſt, have refuſed to Subſcribe.</hi>
                           <pb n="188" facs="tcp:38071:98"/> Confidence may be a bolſter for any thing; otherwiſe I am more inclined to credit thoſe whoſe care it was to propoſe the Oath to be ſubſcribed by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of <hi>Sorbon,</hi> than theſe Cavillers who are ignorant of the whole tranſaction. Now they do poſitively affirm that none of the Six Profeſſors did ever refuſe, nor was any of them conſulted but <hi>Monſieur Le Stocque,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Deperire,</hi> both which notwithſtanding offered to ſign in caſe it had been propoſed unto them by Authority. And, as for <hi>Monſieur Perot,</hi> in whom theſe Cavillers ſo much glory, he has declared in the preſence of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſons of quality of our own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who conſulted him about it, that this Oath may with a ſafe Conſcience be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and that he cenſured no body for it; for which reaſon our Catechiſt, in one of his laſt prints proclaims him to <hi>be now byaſſed.</hi> As to thoſe other Divines, when I know who and what they are I ſhall make reply; in the mean time, if they pleaſe, they may be convinced by the Subſcription it ſelf that ſeveral of the Regulars have alſo ſigned, and I may with truth add that few or none, to whom it was propoſed have refuſed to ſubſcribe.</p>
                        <pb n="189" facs="tcp:38071:98"/>
                        <p> The concluſion is, <hi>that neither the most famous nor the moſt ancient of the</hi> Sorbon <hi>have ſubſcribed.</hi> As to this I muſt refer the Reader to thoſe who have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be acquainted with the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Univerſity and the reſt of the Subſcribers, who are all living, and moſt of them reputed the very Flower of the <hi>Sorbon.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. <hi>Line</hi> 14. to Sale. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 6. Allegiance. <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>l.</hi> 7. Oath-teachers. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 20. Arms. <hi>p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 9. Moral Certainty. <hi>p.</hi> 84. <hi>l.</hi> 4. proceed upon. <hi>p.</hi> 89. <hi>l.</hi> 5. Papiſt. <hi>p</hi> 99. <hi>l.</hi> 23. Heiſſius. <hi>p.</hi> 128. <hi>l.</hi> 11. upon by.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
